Jim Hollis, this incredible young
psychoanalyst, came on the podcast. He
basically nailed it. He said, "You have
to shut up, suit up, and show up. Stop
complaining. Somebody's definitely
suffering more than you. Be grateful for
something. You're alive. You have to get
to that level when you're suffering."
>> And he explains how critical this is to
our psyche, how critical it is to our
feelings of selfworth. And then he also
has this other thing about how
critically important it is to ideally
once a day, but at least a few times a
week to get out of the stimulus and
response that is, you know, shut up,
suit up, show up, and really touch into
what's true for you, like what he calls
your heart's desires. Well, you know,
why don't we just do a quick call back?
The Dark Wizard. This sounds like an
Aussie Osborne album, but it's not. is a
documentary and we were [clears throat]
chatting about it before we started
recording since it's top of mind. Why
don't you just describe what that's
about because this involves a character
that I tracked for a super long time.
>> Teen Potter.
>> Teen Potter. So, what is The Dark
Wizard? Why why has it struck you so?
>> Okay. So, I learned about this movie
from Andy Stumpf, who's a former, well,
retired Navy Seal tier one operator who
then set two world records with the Red
Bull High Performance team doing
>> wing suiting,
>> base jumping, wing suiting, whatever you
want to call the squirrel suit.
>> Squirrel suit. and he told me about this
movie, The Dark Wizard, which is about
Dean Potter, who started off as a
climber and then became, people can
watch the documentary, and then got into
parachuting and then what he called
freebasing, which was, you know,
climbing and then jumping off a rock and
parachuting and then eventually wing
suiting. And I won't give away anymore,
but it's a really interesting four-part
series that gets into his mental health
challenges,
>> how he was able to funnel, let's just
call them, the high dopamine, more manic
states
>> into incredible feats of performance,
and then how he balanced out the lows.
But the most interesting part about it
to me is at the level of something I
think about a lot these days, which is
energy. like we're born into this world
with a certain amount of energy and we
think about it as time and longevity,
but there are people that seem to I
don't want to give anything away here
>> about the movie, but there are people
that seem to have more of this thing
that we call energy. And when they're
able to focus it, they take performance
to just outrageously high levels. And
you see how the energy folds back on him
and almost destroys him at times. and
also times when he's somehow able to
harness it and put it to these
incredible feats. But the most important
thing about the film is he talks about
and he demonstrates
through the activities I talked about
before wing suiting etc. He demonstrates
how when you are in competition with
other people it's a misuse of the energy
that can harm you. But when you are
seeking what he calls just seeking
beauty, like really trying to chase the
feeling, the pure experience of taking
that energy and putting it into
something that you love, that's when the
really impressive feats land and that
move you forward. So there does seem to
be something almost spiritual about
whether or not we're funneling energy
into things that really reflect us at
our best. Mhm.
>> what he calls funneling into beauty
versus competition. And competition is,
it turns out, is what destroys people.
And everyone will say, "No, no, no. It's
actually what what allows you to reach a
higher and higher bar. But if you watch
all four episodes, you realize, no,
actually, that's an illusion.
>> And when you get caught in that, you're
limiting your output. You're limiting
your performance." It also has multiple
cameos by the great Alex Honold, and
their competition is extremely
interesting. So, I'll leave it at that.
That's a long teaser, but it's a real
insight into human psychology and
energy, which is something again I'm
just obsessed with because ultimately
it's where we place our efforts at
Foundation.
>> That's all we've got. That's all we've
got.
>> And Dean Potter also fascinating
character. I'm going to watch this. And
if people have enjoyed slacklining, he
helped to popularize slacklining
certainly as cross trainining for
climbing. But overall, and I can't help
but mention the incredible Lar Hamilton
also cuz we're sitting here in Malibu.
So if anybody's ever done
>> stand up paddle boarding, e- foiling,
fewer people will have done towin
surfing certainly, but people should
watch I think it's riding giants about
the early chapters of layered and
standup paddle boarding goes way back,
probably thousands of years, but he
certainly helped to repopularize it. We
are going to talk about all sorts of
frontier topics. We're going to talk
about perhaps some revisions,
>> updates maybe a better way to put it.
>> Yep. And I'm just gonna hop into this
very long list that we will almost
certainly not complete. But let's let's
hop into one that is of personal
interest to me.
And I want to hear how this experience
informed your training. Dorian Yates. So
I have interviewed Dorian, but I've
never met him. You had the chance to
train with Dorian.
>> He is multiple time Mr. Olympia.
>> Six. Yep.
>> Six times. He was legendary not only for
his accomplishments in bodybuilding but
also for in the eyes of many the
bizarness of his training methods which
which in contrast to many were pretty
minimalist in certain respects. So could
you just speak to the experience of
training with Dorian and what you took
away from that in terms of application
to your own training? Yeah, I've had the
honor and pleasure and pain of training
with Dorian Yates once here in Los
Angeles. We did a back workout back and
rear delts workout and then I just came
back from Marbella, Spain where we train
legs together and it's the sorest I've
ever been. And I should say the science
caught up to Dorian.
What Dorian did to train for Mr. Olympia
and what Mike Menser, who I'll explain
in a moment, were proponents of is now
very well supported by the peer-reviewed
data. And a bunch of physio folks are
probably jumping out of their seats
going, "No, no, you don't have to go to
failure beyond failure, and you actually
need more sets." Not all. Ah, but if you
look at their training, which was
essentially a couple of warm-ups, a
light set to just familiarize yourself
with a movement, a medium set, maybe
like 50% of what you would use on your
work set, work set somewhere between,
you know, five and 12 repetitions
typically, and then maybe a third
warm-up for just a couple of reps, kind
of practice sets. And then Menser, Mike
Menser, was a big proponent of one
allout set to failure.
>> Mhm. Turns out that's probably not
enough for most people to stimulate
hypertrophy and strength increases
because it demands so much focus,
intensity, and effort. There's a kind of
a systemic neural fatigue to it. And a
lot of people just can't contract the
muscles with with enough focus and
intensity for one set to absolute
failure to work. Dorian basically is
more proponent of two sets per exercise,
maybe two or three exercises per major
body part. Major body part being quads,
not legs, right? So,
training with Dorian essentially
consists of what I just described, a
couple of warm-ups, two allout sets to
failure or one set and then some
assisted reps or a drop set or a rest
pause where you, you know, rest after
failure and then do a couple more reps.
Now, what's unique about that training
is
you feel very tired at the end of a
workout, but a couple hours later you're
fine.
>> And indeed, if you do it right, you get
stronger. every single workout with the
caveat and Dorian made this clear to me
that about every six or eight weeks or
so you need to come off the gas pedal a
bit and just stay out of the gym for a
week or you kind of do a kind of more
moderate week. Now what Menser and let's
just stick with what Dorian said because
it's let's call it lowish volume high
intensity. What he's a proponent of was
heresy back in the day. Certainly the
opposite extreme would be like the
Schwarzenegger two hours twice a day
type workouts and then people will say
well Dorian was using loads of steroids
and growth hormone etc. The scientist in
me will in no attempt to defend him will
just accurately say what's the one thing
that he was doing differently.
>> Yeah that was part like everyone was and
is taking some testosterone and other
anabolics androgenics and some were
taking growth hormone but the point is
and at the top level all of those guys
have incredible genetics long muscle
bellies. What makes Dorian, even now at
65, he carries a ton of muscle mass.
He's most he's doing a lot of biking,
he's doing functional training, he's
doing a lot of other things, but just
the sheer density of muscle that he's
carries speaks to his genetics and the
amount of training. What I've been doing
for years is the same split. Three days
a week, one day legs including calves.
Rest a day or two. Train chest and back.
Rest a day shoulders and arms and also
some neck training cuz I didn't wrestle.
And you know neck is important to train
especially for guys.
>> Otherwise it looks like the wrong head
is on a on the body. And also as the
upper spine it's important for shoulder
stability etc. But that split most
people say that doesn't square with the
science. What does the science say? The
science says, and this is Brad
Shenfield's work and other people's
work, which is fantastic, which is when
you stimulate a muscle to grow, you have
about 48 to 72 hours in which there's
protein synthesis after the training.
>> Mhm.
>> So, the logic says, well, logically
speaking, you would say, okay, well,
then train every muscle group three
times a week
>> or twice a week. The problem is that
when you do that, you're not taking into
account the other things that you might
be doing. Like, I run three times a
week. one long slow run for about 60
minutes, one high-intensity interval
type training, you know, like sprint for
30 seconds on the assault bike, rest for
30 seconds, and just repeat that six to
eight times, right? Kind of a max heart
rate training, and then maybe one
moderate session of like 20 or 30
minutes of running or biking.
>> If you're doing those other things, you
have to take that into account. And so
what ends up happening if you do this
split of training your legs, taking a
day off, then the next day doing some
sort of, you know, chest back workout,
the next day running for 30 minutes.
Now, your legs, if you train them
properly, are still probably a little
bit sore.
>> Mhm.
>> You go, okay, well, it's not going to
stimulate hypertrophy, but if then you
do a a bike highintensity workout,
you're getting some some stimulus to
your legs. it's enough to carry you to
the next week. So in reality, this
arrangement of three times per week of
resistance training, three times a week
of cardio, you're training everything
directly once a week and indirectly a
second time and you're getting a lot of
cardio. So because all these studies of
hypertrophy and strength training, it's
on a background typically of not doing
any cardio. And so when I look at like
kind of what the science says, of course
it's people are saying, oh, anywhere
from 10 to 20 work sets per week that to
maximize hypertrophy. Okay, 10 sets of
quads per week distributed into two or
three different sessions plus I'm
supposed to sprint
>> outside or on the on the aerodyine bike
plus I'm supposed to do a long run. All
of a sudden you have a collisions all
over the place. So turns out that for
years I was doing this split and then
when I talked to Dorian he's like yeah
that's more or less what I did when he
split things up into a 4-day split.
Wasn't doing quite as much cardio. He's
like yeah it makes perfect sense. Once
directly, high intensity, lowish volume,
once indirectly like when you train your
chest and back, you're hitting your
arms. Then you train your arms directly.
So it's twice a week. [snorts] When you
do the aine bike, there's some stimulus
of like your lats and pushing and
pulling. Again, it's not for
hypertrophy, but it gets you to the next
week. And what I found from training
with Dorian is you think you're training
to failure. You're not training to
failure. And this is the other piece.
People will say, "Oh, the data say two
or three sets taken two like one or two
reps in reserve." Yeah, it's true. You
can get a lot of hypertrophy and
strength increases doing that. Maybe
it's less taxing on the nervous system,
but what is failure? Like if somebody
really put a gun to your head and said,
"Curl that bar one more time or I'm
going to kill your family." You'd curl
the bar. Now, it's not pleasant nor is
it appropriate to think that way in the
gym. And probably some guys thinking
that way in the gym. It's just
impossible to generate that kind of
mental intensity. So you go, "All right,
if you just step back, the way Dorian is
training now, the way he basically
trained for the Olympia, six Olympia
wins, is you train each body part
directly once per week. It gets hit
indirectly a second time per week. You
give it plenty of rest. You're doing
four to eight sets per body part, two to
three exercises per body part. So you're
splitting up those work sets, you know,
yeah, it all kind of works out." And so
this is the the big revision for me is
if you just look at the science, you'd
say, "Okay, 10 to 20 sets, more volume
of these sets almost to failure or even
to failure is maximizing hypertrophy."
Yeah. If you're doing curls and leg
extensions for a study,
>> but what about all the other stuff?
>> Yeah, for sure.
>> Okay, so that's the gist of it. If you
want to look back at this approach to
training, I mean, there are a lot of
examples, but you can go back to Arthur
Jones. Yep. Then Mike Mensner.
>> Y
>> and then of course you have Dorian Blood
and Guts. I remember having that black
and white book
>> that describes some of the training. And
>> for those who may doubt the efficacy of
this type of let's just call it short
duration because you can do what Dorian
recommended. The workouts can be quite a
bit shorter. And in some with a warm-up
it ends up being you do a couple minutes
on the bike, you do your warm-up sets.
By the time you get to the second or
third exercise for a given body part,
you're only doing one warm-up.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. And what I would say is you can
look at now this is somewhat of a
complicated case study but like Casey
Vader with Arthur Jones crazy example
there's some sort of muscle memory which
we won't get into right now that enabled
a lot of those gains but suffice to say
like this type of minimalist training
can be applied in a lot of places and
the I think according to many
competitive powerlifters the best
powerlifter of all time Ed Conn also
pretty similar recovery schedule, right?
And very interestingly similar in terms
of overlap with durian. So what does
your split look like now? So the split I
follow now is essentially the same one
I've always followed and it is and I
want to be clear why I'm saying Monday
or Tuesday because there needs to be
flexibility in one schedule too. This is
important. So, Monday or Tuesday, I
train my legs,
>> calves, hamstrings, quads, maybe some
direct like glute training, but probably
not.
Couple warm-ups, two to three maybe, but
usually just two hard sets to failure.
If I have a training partner, there may
be some assisted reps. So, quads would
be two working sets of leg extensions.
I'll leave out the warm-ups. Two to
three cuz I'm need a bit more there.
Lying hamstring curls to failure. Then
belt squat. My favorite movement. I
actually bought a belt squat machine
because you don't have to load the
shoulders.
>> Which machine do you like?
>> I use the pitch shark and Rogue's got
now one that's kind of more of a
fan-based one. And there are a bunch of
It's a lot of fun to go on Instagram and
some of the the gym equipment assessment
accounts as a whole world. Sorinx has
one. There are all sorts of great ones
out there. I bought the Pitch Shark.
>> I'll reinforce the belt squat.
>> Love the belt squat. It takes a little
bit getting used to because some people
feel as if, you know, it's like jamming
into their hips or something. You can
put a towel there if you need to. I
mean, all the Westside barbell guys
would talk about belt squat. They would
load it up. You can actually march with
it to build build all sorts of
stabilizing muscles. I mean, that's an
incredible cardio workout. You just put
a couple plates on each side and you and
you just march lifting your knees and
like after like a minute, you're like,
"This is this is no way I can continue.
This a great workout." But I end up
doing leg extensions, leg curls, then
belt squat, and then I may throw in a
couple work sets of hack squat and
that's it. And that's Monday or Tuesday.
The day after legs is always a rest day.
Like if you train legs properly, the
next day should be a rest day. You
should need it. Ideally, I would do
sauna and cold that day.
>> These days, I haven't had time. A day
later, I pick systemically, you have to
ask yourself, am I systemically
exhausted? My did my nervous system take
enough of an ass beating on that Monday
or Tuesday that I need two days off
after legs? And if it was very, very
intense, then I'll do some sort of 20 or
30 minute cardio. Typically, it's a run,
not an allout run, not a jog, just
somewhere in between. Probably in the
zone, let's just call it zone 3ish, zone
3, four. Okay? So, you're not sucking
for air, but it's not a sprint workout.
It's not zone two. And then I'll do a
push pull. I'll do a chest and back
workout and neck.
>> What do you use for neck?
>> I have a 4A neck machine.
>> You do? I do. Which brand do you use?
>> Hammer strength.
>> Hammer strength. Yeah. And again, the
reason I'm asking this guys is not to
plug particular manufacturers because
the physics and the geometry and so on
really matters. It really matters.
>> Especially in my experience with
something that has injury potential. I
have a four-way neck machine also.
>> Oh, cool.
>> I do it very very slowly myself. Like
don't overdo it. If you've never trained
neck, do not rush into like high
velocity stuff, but that's why I was
asking it.
>> Neck is very important. I'll talk about
specifically what I'll do if I don't
have access to that. Some people be like
chest and back same day and rear delts.
And yeah, I think of it as like a torso
workout
>> because I'm not a bodybuilder. I'm
interested in posture. I'm interested in
strength. And I'll I essentially do some
sort of pushing movement like a low
incline press and then some sort of fly
type movement. Although sometimes I'll
just do low incline bench press for so
couple warm-ups, two or three warm-ups,
two or three work sets
>> in the failing somewhere between five
and 12 repetitions.
>> Mhm. And then dips. Weighted dips. Big
believer in these. Like I think it's
like an upper body squat, whatever that
means. Weighted dips typically with a
weight vest. And it looks ridiculous.
But the chains are great if you can
throw those on cuz you can like toss one
off and then keep going if you if you
want to keep going. Whereas if you got a
weight hanging between your legs, which
always just feels weird to me anyway.
You're like waddling around the gym.
It's clanking into your ankles. I'll do
some sort of dip. And then I'll do some
sort of row for the back. Typically like
a low row or a dumbbell row, one arm
dumbbell row. and then some sort of
chinning movement, although I put the
chins first because we've all got this
thing of how many can I do? And I
recently bought a Nautilus pullover
machine based on the training with
Dorian. And it's from 1976 and it's one
of only two that still exist. And it's
kind of like some guys like muscle cars.
I like old school strength training
equipment.
>> Dorian loves his pullovers just like
Arthur Jones.
>> And by the way, if you're rowing heavy
and you're doing these things, you're
getting some forearm training. Mhm.
>> But then I'll do the neck training and
I'll either use the four-way neck
machine. Jeff Cavalier from Athlete X
has a great video on how to train with a
plate. You wrap it in a a train neck
with a plate and a bench. So you could
do that anywhere. You wrap it in a
towel. You lie on your side and you're
just you have to be careful about
closing the chain. So you you know you
got one leg down and you got a hand down
on the ground. The video describes it.
Maybe we could put a link to it. One
thing that's very important I learned
about training neck is you need to nasal
breathe the whole time. have your tongue
on the roof of your mouth and make sure
that you're not sticking your chin out
at any point while you're bending it to
the side because then you start getting
clicking in your jaw. And my spinal
surgeon friends tell me that it's a
great way to slip a disc in your in your
neck. The neck aesthetically, like
people don't, it's always weird when
like dudes are talking about aesthetics
like but these days because of the looks
maxing thing and all [snorts] that like
it's it seems to be like more of But
there's something actually very
important to
>> You're not hammering your cheekbones.
No, I'm definitely hing my [laughter]
cheekbones.
>> Come on, Andrew.
>> Nope. Not hammering my cheekbones. I
mean, you know, that is such a wild
thing. Yeah. No, no, no, no. But there
is something interesting. So, from a
strength and stability standpoint,
training one's neck is really important
because it's the upper spine and it I do
think it's one of the reasons I've never
had any shoulder issues and I've got
long arms and everything points to the
fact that I should have rotator cuff
issues. I don't do any direct rotator
cuff work. I think it's because I
started training my neck a long time ago
and aesthetically like you have this
this is a great opportunity to point out
just how uh perfectly constructed you
are Tim Ferrris you train your neck
really if you look ahead at a male face
>> if the neck sort of arrives right at the
sort of like outer right
>> more or less right you know plus or
minus a few whatever millimeters and
more or less at the outer jaw the
outermost point of the jaw below the
ears like touching there you'll notice
like it it looks kind of right.
>> When somebody is really wide and their
neck is not at that point, it looks like
the wrong head was placed on a body.
Then you see Lar Hamilton and you
realize like this dude just has a a
really big neck, but it's appropriate
for his for his body structure. And then
after the neck, so I'll do I don't know
three sets or two work sets per side.
Although you don't train neck the same
way, like to like four reps and all
that. And then I'll do some core work.
And the core work that I'm a big fan of
because you also get some forearm work
in is I'll hang from a bar and I'll do
some lsits
>> and if I've been doing them a lot
lately, I'll do some pikes. Five sets of
five piking your ankles up to your hands
and then slow on the descent and then
into an LSIT if I can. And I'll do maybe
three or five sets depending and then
lower back work. And I have a 45 degree
angle hyperextension and I'm not taking
that to failure. The low back thing is
really important. I found that and there
are a lot of data out there that if you
can strengthen the spinal erectors, your
posture is better, you're more injury
resistant, but that whole workout takes
an hour tops.
>> Mhm.
>> The next day is the highintensity cardio
day, just max heart rate. These days I
got get on an aerodyine bike and I would
say for this for people it's whatever
you can do without getting hurt.
>> So question for you on the aerodyine or
I guess probably
>> assault bike. This is a digression, so I
won't indulge us too far, but to figure
out why the assault bike worked and
caught on where the aerodyine did not,
right? You can look at footage from Dan
Gable, legendary wrestler, working out
on an aerodyine, but it never really
spread until the assault bike
reformatted it, improved it in some
ways. My question for you on that real
quick for people who don't know, you're
using your arms on these sort of
isolateral movable handles that power
this fan. So you can pedal and use your
arms
>> one or the other or both.
>> And I find that my upper body fatigues a
lot faster than my lower body if I'm
trying to do, let's say, like a
Norwegian 4x4 or something like that,
like 4 minutes on, 3 minutes off, or
four minutes on, four minutes off.
Do you find that not to be the case for
yourself or how do you approach it?
Because I've wanted to use the assault
bike. It's now easier to find an assault
bike in say a hotel gym for me than a
stationary bike that fits well
otherwise. How do you approach that?
>> Well, the naming piece is interesting
and maybe we get into this at some point
deeper in the discussion, but naming is
very important and it's not just
important in health and fitness and this
kind of thing. It's it's actually very
important in science and I'm a you know
a student of science as a field not just
the field of neuroscience in terms of
the facts but also you look at the
culture of a scientific field oftent
times the naming is what carries a field
forward very quickly and you go how can
that be aren't these scientists
shouldn't they just be focused on the
data nomenclature is important because
if more people are doing something
>> because they can talk about it to more
people using the language. It tends to
accelerate a field. Sure. Um, also
assault bike sounds cool. Stationary
bike feels like you're just pedaling.
The assault bike is interesting because
I also I get like a lot of lat work from
it. Keep in mind the day before I
trained my chest and back.
>> No, exactly. That's why I'm asking.
>> So, it ends up being a second kind of
stimulus, not a hypertrophy workout, but
you you sort of end up feeling like
almost like a a pump type thing
>> if you do it right. I can't do more than
30 seconds on, 30 seconds off without
experiencing what you experience, which
is that my legs just have all this gas
and my arms, they can just keep going.
It all transfers to the upper body. So,
Norwegian 4x4
>> on on the assault bike just sounds like
torture to me.
>> This workout, if I can, I'll get outside
and sprint.
>> Mhm.
>> And you could do it on a rower. You
could sprint. You know, I think it's
just important because it's a near
allout or allout workout, 30 seconds on,
30 seconds off. Or maybe you jog a
couple laps and then you do a couple,
you know, you do a 400 on the track and
then walk a lap and then do a 400.
Whatever you do for this workout, you
know, you can come up with any number of
different variations. It's got to be
something where you can apply max effort
and not get hurt.
>> Yeah.
>> And then the next day is a shoulders,
arms. You do some sort of pressing. I'm
not big on lateral raises, some sort of
press for the shoulders, you know,
couple work sets of bicep curls, couple
incline curls, some hammer curls, some
overhead tricep extension for the long
head, couple work sets, some bench dips,
and there you go, like bench dips again.
So now you're getting a little bit of
>> other stuff working even though it's not
a allout chest and back workout. And
then the next day, which is typically on
a Sunday, I'll do some long slow
movement, ideally outside. Maybe it's a
walk and a hike with my girlfriend.
Maybe it's I'm rucking and listening to
a podcast if I'm alone. Maybe I'm
jogging in the sand. Like it could be a
long bike ride. Just something like
there's something so nice just starting
the week.
>> Jogging in the sand sounds miserable for
long.
>> Slow. It's a slow plot. You're a mule. I
like to think of like you're kind of a
mule or I'm a mule.
>> That's going to be my clip for the
teaser
>> with the [laughter] mule.
>> I'm a mule. No, I'm kidding. Cool. No,
that works. That works. That works for
me. And you know, the real hard part
about that workout is not going faster.
>> It's pretty easy to jog and then walk.
Jog and then walk. is probably
beneficial. Yeah.
>> But that workout is as much for the
mental stimulation, but it's also
there's something so nice about going
into the work week.
>> Maybe it lands on a Monday, I don't
know, but typically for me it lands on a
Sunday because there's something so nice
about going to the work having spent as
much time as possible moving outdoors
the day before. But I do this and it
ends up being six workouts a week, but
some are very, very short. None of the
resistance training stuff is terribly
long. You're done in an hour. So unless
you're waiting for equipment and you
know at 50 I'm continuing to you know
get stronger. I'm not you know
outrageously so and it just works. It
just works and it's worked for everyone
that I know. Now one key thing and a lot
of people will what I call they'll kind
of geek this and they won't do compound
movements. You can't do lateral raises
and and I do some rear delt flies on the
whatever one or the either chest and
back day or the shoulders and arms day.
You need that for shoulder posturally,
aesthetically, etc. But people think,
"Oh, I can do leg extensions, leg curls
to failure once a week." No, you're also
hack squatting and belt squatting or hat
squatting and front squatting to failure
for a couple sets.
>> That's intense. You need to do the
compound movements. There's no world
where you can just, you know, do
isolation movements this way. And that's
the thing that sometimes gets forgotten
in the Yates style training. he was
doing a lot of compound movements and
he's still a proponent of that.
>> Well, let's let's hop around and we may
come back to training.
We spoke some time ago about
psychedelics with a focus on MDMA and it
seems like you may have some revised
views, maybe a few caveats. I would be
interested to hear your current
thinking. So, this is an area you've
spoken about and and thought about
pretty extensively and and or as I'm
more of a newbie, as we talked about
last time, in case people didn't hear
that conversation, you know, growing up,
I made the mistake, it was a truly a
mistake of taking some psychedelics at a
at a very young age, quote unquote
recreationally,
LSD,
>> psilocybin, not giving any thought to
like what the long-term consequences
might be. Fortunately, I didn't feel any
long-term consequences, but I had to
enough bad trips, meaning one.
Robin Carter Harris would say, "You
can't have a bad trip. There's no that
you can have a bad trip, Robin. I've had
one. It sucks. You're in the pit for
hours and hours. There's no guide there
if you're doing it recreationally as a
teen. The brain is hyperlastic." It made
me very, very cautious, almost paranoid
about psychedelics for many, many years.
Then also the last time we spoke I
talked about how in an effort to resolve
what I felt were some long-standing
psychological traumas I did clinically
supported MDMA standard kind of MAPS
protocol like take forget the milligram
dosage maybe take like
>> probably 125 something like that
>> yeah and sometimes there's a booster
about 90 minutes in you have someone
there you're doing talk therapy before
during and after tremendously helpful to
be able to feel my feelings to be able
to recognize
what a whole body feeling was about. I
mean, there was never the experience for
me of wanting to
dance or have sex while I was on. It was
like, no, there was some shaking. There
was some a little bit of that, but it
was a very, you know, it's an
impathogen, I think, as you know, it's
not a psychedelic, technically an
impathogen, and raises both dopamine and
serotonin simultaneously, which is very
unusual for any compound to do, and
raises oxytocin quite dramatically. The
data actually say the impathogenic
effect of MDMA is not due to oxytocin
through a kind of sort of good control
where you just give oxytocin and you
don't get the same clinical effects. But
you could argue the cocktail effect, the
synergy might be important. So I did
that a few times. I think it was a total
of four times separated by a number of
months or a year clinically supported.
In any event, after a period of doing
that, I took a break and
on the suggestion of the same clinical
group decided to partake in a psilocybin
experiment and it was highdos
psilocybin. Now psilocybin as you know
leads to I think in the words of our
friend Paul Kiy it almost like recedes
the waterline on the on the unconscious
mind. So what I found in psilocybin was
because my brain often thinks in
analogies like this just how I structure
my thinking it's reflexive for me offs
psilocybin almost everything that came
to me in those sessions was kind of
symbolic representation analogies for
somebody else who who represents their
world not that way maybe musically or
through sematic experience it's likely
that from my understanding that they
will experience insights
through those same kind of
representations.
What I found from psilocybin
work was
it was exquisite at revealing to me the
structure of my thinking and the ways
that some of the patterns in my life
that were not serving me well
how they were structured. It was sort of
like oh coming out of it there's a like
wow there's this form of self seduction
that I do which takes actually eight
forms which
look the following way in my life I can
be seduced by the enchantment of some
sort of promise of a future outcome
that's not realistic and you can see
that I'm just kind of giving one example
and once you see that you can't unsee it
and that for me was an incredible
experience I do think it was important
to keep a journal afterwards to take
notes while off
the drug. And for me that was very very
helpful at allowing me to understand the
structure of my thinking both for things
that serve me and don't serve me. I will
say and this is getting a little you
know well as long as people are doing
like live streams of taking psychedelics
I feel very I feel on very solid ground
but who knows.
>> Well just wait until the second half of
this conversation.
>> Yeah. Exact. [laughter] Exactly. I mean
I don't want anyone to run out and take
these things without clinical support.
There are a number of people who
shouldn't be taking them and all the
usual caveats apply young people etc.
But the real like wo
one session type rewiring which was the
hardest work I've ever done having done
lots and lots of therapy. But the
hardest work I've ever done was to take
MDMA
and then a couple hours later take a
high dose of psilocybin. And I've only
done that twice. By the way, if I ever
try and run for public office, any
mistakes I make, they'll attribute to
this. By the way, I've seen that
publicly. But I'm going to make it very
clear right now. Not only am I not going
to run for office, I'm running from
office. So, you know, there's been some
speculation, but the interesting thing
was no two days later drop, which you do
experience with MDMA. I just did not
experience that if I took psilocybin
with it. Remarkable. Had some of my best
workouts, work weeks, etc. It's like, oh
wow, that can be avoided through this
thing. But what was remarkable is on
MDMA as an impathogen, you feel very
good about most anything you focus on.
You can find the peace in it. You can
find the love in it. Could be this yerba
mate, which I happen to love, but you
like would really love. That's the
danger, right? You can get pulled into
these force fields of thinking
something's really important. It might
not be that important when the session
is over. That's why I think it's very
important to have a trained guide with
you.
But there's the drop.
Psilocybin for me was a very dark and
harrowing experience.
>> Lot of purging, a lot of vomiting.
>> Really
>> about halfway through.
>> These weren't enormous doses. They
weren't small either. It was 4 to 5 g.
>> Just to be clear for folks. Yeah. Of
dried like silos mushrooms.
>> So for me,
>> it was terrifying to be on psilocybin
alone. It was extremely difficult. And
the combination of the two, it was sort
of like having my really good friend Rob
Moore in there with me going, "You can
do this." Now, Rob wasn't in there,
[laughter] so I'm just sort of half
joking because he's here in the room
with us now, but it was like, "I can do
this. I can lean into the hardest work."
I'm going to give an example so it's not
too vague.
>> Yeah.
>> I'd spent a fair amount of time thinking
about some of the harder things that had
happened in my childhood, in my life.
Some of which were self-inflicted, some
of which were not self-inflicted.
And I'd come to peace
about those through the work I describe
standard psychotherapy lot of journaling
time MDMMA psilocybin those separately
taking them together I had this voice in
my head that was like it's time to do
the real work and I was like oh goodness
>> and I said out loud like I don't want I
thought we're just going to like listen
to Grateful Dead today and you know the
person helping me was like no that's not
how this works. You know that. And I'm
thinking, I don't want to do this. I
really And I don't even know what this
is. I just know there's something there
that's
>> And I'm like, oh [__] And I think it is
important for people to understand this
cuz it is it can be very, very scary and
you feel it sort of coming at you like a
storm and you can push it away. I could
have spent the entire time listening to
the Grateful Dead. Not a huge Grateful
Dead fan, but you know, people have
encouraged me to listen to it, so I've
been doing it. I like it. But I could
have done that, but I didn't. Instead, I
was like, "Okay,
with those two compounds in me, I was
like, I can do this. I've got myself
held. Like, I'm my own friend. That's
the impathogen. I can do this." It
wasn't this like, "All right, let's go.
Like, let's fight." And that session
took me through a brutally hard voyage
of thinking about all the things that
didn't happen, all the things that I
would
wish had happened.
>> Mhm.
>> That I was in no position to make happen
for myself. Heavy, gnarly. And coming
through it, it was the perfect thing
because I was like, those are the things
I know I can create now.
>> There is no way, and this is why I feel
it's important to talk about these
compounds. There is no way whatsoever
that a therapist was going to sit down
and go, "Hey,
what's ever on your mind today? Let's
talk about what didn't happen. No one's
ever done that for And if they had,
there's no way that I would have been in
the full emotional experience of the
lack
>> or necessarily had access to it
>> or had access to it. Right? So, I give
that as an example. It's certainly not
what everyone would experience, but I'd
never thought about the problem of what
hadn't happened as a as a viable option
to explore. It's so obvious now. But
then the outcome of this brutally hard
session was beautiful. No additional
drug, nothing for and it stayed with me.
This was over well over a year ago. And
I thought, "This is awesome. I can
create these things. I know exactly what
to aim for." And it started to make
steps in my life, you know, steering the
ship in those directions. And not
surprisingly, it's like, "Yeah, I can do
this. I can do these things. I need some
practice." And and so I think that the
medicines, as we think of them, are
immensely powerful, immensely
precarious. You need the support.
I've been told in these sessions, hey,
maybe we don't go there. You don't go
there. that feels like a repeat. You
know, you need someone to help guide
you. These are not to be used
recreationally in my opinion. At least
not for folks like me. You know, I'm
just not interested in that.
>> But the lessons I learned is the
following.
>> Neuroplasticity is the goal.
>> Directed toward something that often
times we can't identify
through standard therapy. Like you could
say, "Oh, I'm trying to resolve my
traumas." That's a sentence. If you
can't know exactly what the thing was
and or even if you can or the things
that happened, what what about the
things that didn't happen? It just never
would have occurred to me. So, it
revealed both the thing that needed work
and allowed me to do a lot of the work
in real time and spit me out the other
end, which is how it felt. You know, I
wasn't cratered coming out the other. I
was like, that was an ass kicking of a
whole other level. And like with a clear
mission in mind of what to do in my
daily life that has served me very, very
well. It also reminded me that we seem
to have this one compound type view and
I'm not suggesting that
polyfarmarmacology is the way but it
turned out in this case was the
appropriate tool for me
>> and it's also a reminder that combined
pharmarmacology with brain machine
interface and stimulation combining
ketamine therapy with TMS. I've not done
ketamine nor TMS, but
I think we are entering a really
exciting new time where we're going to
be able to amplify
the effects of machines and drugs. Let's
call them what they are. It's
pharmarmacology, but drugs that they can
synergize in ways that are more
directed.
>> But ultimately, the the directives in
life are what matter. Like, do I feel
better? What am I doing on a daily basis
that's serving me? Like if the inter
mids singulate cortex or the posterior
insula gets, you know, 10% thicker,
great. But if you're not making better
decisions, like frankly, who gives a
[__] Who cares? So ultimately, everyday
outcomes, the clinical outcomes and
everyday outcomes are what really
matter. Brain imaging is important, too,
of course. So
>> the experience with these with these
compounds, I will also say, left me in a
place where I'm like, I'm feeling pretty
good right now. I I feel really good. In
fact, I don't feel quote unquote called
to it again right now. Maybe I will at
some point.
>> I have not, you know, for instance, I've
never done Iawaska. There seems to be
this resurgence of the oneshot theory in
Silicon Valley that there are these like
CEOs or company founders rather who will
take Iawaska and then like quit the
company or something. And I made the
argument to Mark Andre and like well
maybe they're happier. And he made the
argument quite astutely as pretty much
everything Mark says is he said yeah but
as an investor that's not what I'm
looking for. And I go, well, sure, but
from a life satisfaction point, maybe
yes. I think it depends on what your
incentive structure is.
>> And so I am very excited about
plasticity tools. Whether or not it's
talk therapy combined with a brain
stimulation device that's invasive or
non-invasive or a veagal stimulation
device, those are getting better and
better all the time. whether or not it's
an impathogen and psilocybin
high dose with therapeutic support or
it's daily micro doing for seven days
with an undetectable like subjective
effect where you're just like I feel
fine I feel normal but you're doing a
bunch of hard things and suddenly your
brain is shifting more quickly. I mean I
think this is where the field needs to
go.
>> Yeah.
>> Enough with it quote unquote opens
plasticity.
>> That's a general statement not about
psychedelics but includes psychedelics.
Let me chime in here. This is this is
good terrain. So I would say a couple of
things that might might be helpful for
folks or interesting just to bat around.
So the first I would say is that
when you induce plasticity, let's just
explore that with in the context of
psychedelics and I'm going to use some
pretty primitive
analogies here. But if you're heating up
the clay, that doesn't immediately
mean that in that window of plasticity
or after that, you're going to turn out
better than you were before. You have to
be very cautious about how you reshape
the clay once you induce that
plasticity. And I'd suggest people check
out Gul Dolan. She's at UC Berkeley.
She's looked at critical periods and the
reopening of critical periods after
psychedelics. She's focused a lot on
MDMA but also
is exploring IBA gain among other things
and that's part of the reason why
historically if you talk to facilitators
who have literally supervised thousands
of sessions
more common in like the neocamonic kind
of Northern California context for
simplicity than the indigenous but the 2
to 3 weeks following has always been
viewed as this golden window for
reformatting your behavior. behavior and
your patterns. And it turns out that
modern science, ghoul's research being
one good example of it, reinforces this.
So it's not just taking the medicine in
the form of a pill, a potion, whatever
it might be. It's actually that is a
catalyst that opens a period of time
during which the work needs to be done.
Right? So that's part number one. I
would say that your experience also with
the hippie flipping, so the the MDMA
plus psilocybin or in this case slocity
mushrooms, I would say blunting or
eliminating the let's just call it
energetic hangover MDMA. Super typical.
I don't generally well not that I'm
doing this at all obviously for legal
purposes but let's just say
hypothetically
that's part of the reason why some
people will format say a weekend where
you have
breath work let's just say as a leadin
then in pathogen and then the next day
something that is more and this term is
controversial but classical psychedelic
again for simplicity let's just call it
psilzy LSD whatever it might
also tends to reduce that potential for
like the energetic hangover, right? So
that's pretty common. People can check
out also transcend therapeutics. It just
got acquired or at least the majority
was purchased who have been
commercializing methylone which is a
very very interesting compound. It's
like the shorter acting softer cousin of
MDMA much less body load. Very very
interesting compound. they did which was
very smart and I'm not saying MAPSLOS
whatever the current name is wasn't
smart but one of the problems that MDMMA
ran into is that it was coupled with
psychotherapy and the FDA does not know
how to regulate psychotherapy that they
don't know how to standardize or think
of as standardized and so what
transcended is they just completely
separated the two and actually removed
the psychotherapy completely and said
how do people do with methylone period
that's it and they've done incredibly
well which is reflected in the
acquisition really interesting compound
methylone
>> methylone interesting I I wasn't aware
of it
>> yeah I mean I I think these are very
>> interesting compounds and I used to have
this view like oh psychedel like
>> you're increasing neurom modulators
>> SSRI will do that too differently you
know and clearly a different experience
actually I've not taken SSRIs
Trying to think. Have I ever taken an
SSRI?
>> Have you ever taken Trezadone? It's not
technically an SSRI.
>> No, I haven't. I think there's so much
important work to be done here. And I
will say huge hat tip to you. You've
been ushering this forward. It's amazing
we can even have this conversation,
things that have happened,
>> things have changed.
>> My conclusion after all of that and lots
of personal flight time with lots of
things is that to state the obvious,
it's not a panacea. It's for most people
not going to be one and done where the
potion pill plant medicine does all the
heavy lifting for you. The way I think
about it now is it's like very
complicated knee reconstructive surgery.
It's
>> like you're going to want to pick the
doctor very carefully. You're going to
want to know how to do your due
diligence.
>> You have the surgery and then guess
what? The next let's even could be like
both shoulders, both knees. Boy, do you
have a lot of rehab to do. Y
>> and that's the way that I myself think
about it. And also it's contraindicated
for a lot of people at least as of right
now. There are exclusionary criteria for
these clinical trials. And I don't think
all of them will hold water long term.
But if you have bipolar, if you have a
family history of schizophrenia or
borderline personality disorder, it is
generally not a good idea. And coming
back to the polyfarma, do not
underestimate the risk of cannabis when
taken with or in proximity to these
drugs. You can get yourself into a lot
of trouble. And then I would say to
deliver on the brain stimulation side
that one of the most interesting things
to me right now is the one day protocol.
It's been refined by Dr. Jonathan Downer
at University of Toronto and others but
using an agent in this case an
antibiotic to induce neuroplasticity
called descloerene.
So you take in this case it's just a
coincidence but I think the most common
dose that's been used is 125 milligrams
like oral like troy and you dissolve it
an hour before your stimulation. Again,
I'm pulling this from memory so people
can read up on the literature, but you
take that five-day protocol that had
been compressed by Nolan and team down
from 3 to 6 months. They had compressed
it down to 5 days, but people are still
having to take 5 days off of work
because you're getting stimulated 10
times a day, right? Every hour on the
hour. They're variable protocols, but
that's roughly it. Very few people can
take a week off of work and pay out of
pocket. Incredibly expensive. So this
one day is preloading with the descerion
and you take those five days and you
compress it into one day and I've had
experiences with this one-day protocol
and full disclosure I'm involved with
this company Ampa Health which is
co-founded by Jonathan Downer. So
there's that. But I experienced all this
before any of these conversations. And
from that, I've been able to get like a
90% reduction in my generalized anxiety
disorder and OCD for 3 to four months at
a time. Some people get much longer
durability.
>> That's impressive.
>> I've met people who have had 18 months
of durability with major depressive
disorder, one day. and the side effect
profile
and there are other hardware providers
and so on that you can look into but
having this accelerated TMS protocol
enhanced by the neuroplasticity right of
this descarer DCS for short it's been a
real focus is trying to look at neurom
modulation writ large as opposed to just
psychedelics right because if the only
tool you have is a hammer and it's not
my expression right a lot of things
start to look like nails and
psychedelics are not useful for
everything. They just are not. And if
you look at any historical use of these
compounds, having thousands and millions
of people taking psychedelics is a brand
new experiment. Right? If you look at
most indigenous cultures who consume
whether it's slobby mushrooms or iawaska
or something else, it is a very very
very very small percentage of the
population. Yeah. typically reserved for
who you might consider the ethnobbotnist
pharmacist medicine man or woman and
pre-Colombian contact for instance with
like in the case of Iawaska
two things number one the patients
seldom drank so to the patients in
quotation marks cuz two of the principal
uses of iaska were for warfare and
hunting so this idea of like we just put
LSD or whatever the psychedelic dour is
in the water and we have world peace. It
ain't a real thing, guys.
>> Could be the opposite.
>> Go to any psychedelic conference and
look at the obscene infighting for any
proof of that. You know, it's the worst.
It's so so bad.
What they do, coming back to your point,
right, and alongside the descerion and
many other compounds, is they induce
neuroplasticity, which affords you a
window
of opportunity within which you can do
some pretty cool stuff. Oh, I'm totally
on board. I mean, it's interesting
because as we're sort of moving through
exercise and psychedelics and which is
really a conversation about
neuroplasticity and mental health,
perhaps physical health as well.
>> It's very clear that like all the stuff
about exercise, increasing brain derived
neutropic value, it's
>> all tied together.
>> It's all tied together. And then you
think, well, why is my brain, you know,
sharper after I exercise? There's an
alertness thing. You're using your own
chemistry to wake you up. some BDNF, but
then people sort of assume you just have
to do the exercise part. You actually
have to go try and learn something to
get the plasticity. Doesn't matter. You
could quadruple the amount of
circulating BDNF in your brain.
Nothing's going to change. I know this
for a fact because for years I studied
neuroplasticity. You need precisely
timed neural firing pre- and post
synaptically. You can do this with
sensory input. We're talking about
reading, math, learning divibe code. Is
that what they call it now? Right. Which
Rick Rubin invented. No, I'm kidding. He
did. He's going to kill me for saying
that, but the memes would make you think
so. Whatever it is that you want to
rewire, you have to go do that hard
work. Just getting the chemicals
increase doesn't do it. You need
alertness. You need these chemicals
circulating. It helps to have an
emotional rise. If it's for, you know,
certain kinds of work and perhaps not
for others, more analytic work requiring
probably less of an emotional rise.
But the directed part is that that's the
next step. And I think about that a lot.
I mean, having sat down as you have with
so many guests now who are experts in
psychiatry and psychology and self-help,
for lack of a better way to put it,
it's reassuring to me that as with
exercise, as with nutrition, as with
psychedelics, some kind of themes are
starting to fall out. We're starting to
almost get to principles. There's this
wonderful book in the field of
neuroscience called Principles of
Neuroscience. Almost everyone gets it.
It's a big old
>> I think I had that textbook.
used to be Kendell Jesseline Schwarz and
then one of those folks got cancelled
and then passed away and so it's got a
different author line there but that was
the original one Kendelle Jesseline
Schwarz and the idea is principles of
neuroscience yes it's filled with facts
about receptors and neurotransmitters
and tons of beautiful details of all
these discoveries but what you learn as
a graduate student and a postto and then
when you eventually if you become a
professor you want to teach the students
is what are the principles of how a
nervous system builds itself attractants
and repellents. What are the principles
by which neural circuits change? Oh, you
need coordinated firing. You know, you
can actually unwire things if they're
mismatched firing. Like, how do you
build a memory and then move it
someplace else so you don't have to fill
the memory making area to its capacity?
You know, these are the principles are
what eventually emerge and that's very
useful in the fields, if you will, of
health and wellness, which umbrellas all
the things we've been talking about and
a lot more. We're finally getting to
that. This is the reason why I threw out
like exhale emphasized breathing slows
you down, calms you down and inhale
emphasized breathing wakes you up.
Resistance training to or near or past
failure that kind of scales the number
of sets. We are finally at a place where
because of social media, thank goodness,
because of podcasts, again, huge hat tip
to you. Yours was the first podcast I
ever listened to, still listen to. It
was, you know, we are finally at this
place where people are starting to hear
like, "Yeah, I get it. The sunlight
thing." You go, "You get it? Okay,
cool." Ironically, the things that
people have heard many, many times are
often things they need to do every day
and be reminded of many, many times. But
it's not about getting morning sunlight
for x number of minutes, etc. It's about
understanding what is it in this morning
sunlight thing. I'll tell you right now
the big eye openener for me, no pun
intended, this last year was I did an
episode on cortisol, the quote unquote
stress hormone. No, cortisol is involved
with stress. Yes, that's true. But
cortisol mobilizes glucose from the
liver and elsewhere into the body. It's
an energy deploying hormone. When you
wake up in the morning, it's because of
a rise in cortisol. Cortisol awakening
response. Adenosine is very low.
Melatonin is dropping. Cortisol goes up.
you wake up, if your alarm goes off,
spikes even more. Viewing bright light,
ideally from sunlight first thing in the
morning, increases that morning cortisol
spike by about 50%. Okay? And on and on
and I could say, and also cold water and
caffeine and exercise. Exercise, by the
way, will triple or quadruple your
baseline cortisol levels at any time of
the 24-hour cycle. So, you go, okay,
that's a bunch more facts. Ah, but the
principle is if your morning cortisol is
high and you can make it higher doing
any number of the things I just
described.
It ensures that your evening and
nighttime cortisol is low and that's
what sets you up for an increase in
melatonin. It's what helps ensure a
great night's sleep. And so you go,
okay, so the real principle here is you
want to bookend the day with high
cortisol in the morning, whenever your
morning happens to be. It doesn't matter
if it's 6:00 a.m. or 10:00 a.m. Bright
light, caffeine, hydration, exercise,
a little stress, too probably will help.
And you want the end of your day to be
low cortisol, high melatonin,
high adenosine. You know, the more
movement you get during the day, the
better off you are. And all of a sudden,
it doesn't really matter if you have
access or the time to do all of the
things I just described. It's not about
morning sunlight, per se. Just turns out
that morning sunlight in your eyes is
the best way to ramp up that morning
peak. And that ramped up morning peak is
the best way to make sure that it's low
at night. And if you experience any
stress in the evening at night, it's a
quick blip in cortisol and that's
reduced. Otherwise, it's a blip on top
of a high baseline.
>> You look at cancer treatment outcomes.
You look at anxiety. By the way, what I
just described is true for kids,
pregnant women, permenopausal,
menopausal, and men. You want high
morning, low evening, and nighttime
cortisol. Aim for that that principle.
Whatever you have available to do that.
If you're on a plane, it looks
different. If you're in California, it
looks different than if you're in
Scandinavia, different times of year.
Whatever you do to try and ensure that
bookending, high and low cortisol,
respectively, morning and night, you
won. You won the day and the night. And
so, it doesn't really matter what the
individual protocols are.
>> Mhm. And this to me is like the most
important and exciting thing about where
the quote unquote field of health and
wellness and public discourse about
health has taken us, which is we finally
have some principles to work with. And
then if people go, well, I don't like
the cold shower. Okay, fine. But like, I
don't I don't like resistance training.
I want to do PL. Okay, fine.
>> Choose a different tool.
>> Choose a different tool. But the
principles are what count. And to me,
that's super exciting. That's not
boring. All right, Andrew, I want to ask
you about peptides.
All the rage. You look at Google Trends.
Everybody and their brother has a
peptide startup, but there seems to
maybe be something there. I don't know
if there's a there there. For people who
have heard the word, don't know exactly
what folks are talking about. I get
texted every week multiple times from
people asking about various peptides.
And I'd say half the time, depending on
what they're trying to do, I'm like,
can't you just be a grown-up and inject
testosterone or HGH [laughter]
instead? If you're trying to get there
directly, but I would be very interested
to hear, I know there's a broad spectrum
of stuff that people are experimenting
with,
>> what are these things and and what's
your current thinking?
>> I also don't completely disagree with
you about like just be a grown-up and
take cipionate and HGH. If you want to
maintain fertility, take some HCG as
well.
>> Yeah.
>> And I'm being facitious, of course. I I
think there are risks to all of those,
but it is the appropriate opening joke
slreity because if you're expecting
cipionate HGH type results from
peptides, you ain't going to get them.
At least not with respect to like
anabolic growth, feelings of well-being.
Peptides are short chains of amino
acids. Insulin's a peptide, etc. I
cannot take credit for what I'm about to
say next, but it's a very, very
important principle. I think this is
kind of the theme today I suppose. Abu
Bakri who's an MD came on the podcast
talked about peptides and he said look
for many many hundreds if not thousands
of years but certainly hundreds of years
in the context of pharma
people have been searching for medicines
in plants isolating medicines from
plants. Pharma companies still do this.
Now people are starting to look for
medicines within the body and peptides
are a great example of that. GLP for
instance, the drugs that increase GLP do
so to thousandfold levels over the
levels of circulating GLP that you would
have and they result in as we all know
robust weight loss. So that's one
category. I think we need to think about
categories of peptides but understand
that peptides are all over they're made
in your brain and body. Some of them may
have benefits when made synthetically
and delivered at very very high doses
such as with these GLP agonists ompic
mjaro rea tide is one that we should
talk about made by lily it's coming out
soon
>> it impacts the GLP system but also the
gip and the glucagon system
>> careful with that one kiddos
>> a lot of people are going to be micro
doing it
>> a lot of people are finding that micro
doses can have similar effects and
that's an important kind of cost risk
analysis okay So stepping back, peptides
are made in your body. They at high
concentrations made synthetically they
may provide
benefits that are make them medicines.
So we can think of the weight loss
peptides.
The GLPs being the most prominent
example. The GLP drugs that increased
levels of GLP 100fold were used to treat
diabetes for a while still are, but they
didn't induce much weight loss. the ones
that raise GLOP levels thousandfold or
more, those lead to robust weight loss,
including muscle loss. And so that's
part of the controversy. Also, there's
discussion about maybe increasing some
apathy. They reduce craving for alcohol
and perhaps cravings more generally at
the recommended dosages. In some people,
they can create nausea, which is why
some people are taking less of them and
still getting the weight loss benefits,
but less nausea. There's a lot of stuff
going on there.
to stay on the GLPs and weight loss
peptides. Specifically, Lily developed
reatride which hits the GLP GIP and
glucagon system leads to the most robust
weight loss seems to spare some muscle.
Perhaps people should always resistance
train anyway to offset that. But
it's the most effective of those weight
loss, let's just call it GLPS, even
though it hits these other systems. The
gray market is the quote unquote for
research purposes only stuff that you
can buy online. It's perfectly legal to
sell
for research purposes only, not for
animal or human use. And I joked on X a
while ago like, wow, all these home
labs, everyone's buying this. Of course,
people are injecting them. The concern
is about contamination with things like
lipid polysaccharide or you're not
getting what you think you're getting.
So many people are already taking
redatruide even though it hasn't been
formally released because it's pretty
easy to synthesize. And so it's being
sold on the gray market, people are
taking it. There's a second category and
then I'll return to the kind of gray
market issue. The second category would
be things to increase growth hormone,
so-called growth hormone secrets, things
like serarellin, epomeurlin,
tesamearellin.
These are all varants on the theme of
get the brain neurons that project down
to the pituitary to stimulate release of
growth hormone at night. Typically, you
don't eat a couple hours before sleep is
the idea. Probably good for sleep
anyway. It is good for sleep anyway.
Then you inject this stuff. Typically,
it leads to maybe a three to eightfold
increase in growth hormone IGF-1.
Some stimulate appetite quite a bit like
MK677. Some don't. I've tried Smurellin
very briefly. Dramatically increased my
slowwave deep sleep. Nuked my REM sleep.
This is a common theme. Spiked my
prostate specific antigen. I've never
had any problems with PSA. I came off
it. PSA went back to normal. No one's
been able to give me a mechanistic
explanation for that. I'm not about to
run the experiment again. I didn't find
that I got much fat loss from it, but I
didn't use it very long. I didn't find I
got stronger, you know, just didn't seem
worth it to me given the PSA thing. A
lot of people take these thing and
they're going to get these really
dramatic increases in growth hormone.
They sound dramatic three to eightfold,
but whether or not they're meaningful in
terms of fat loss, it doesn't really
seem they're that robust, especially
given that you have all the GLPS now. So
the growth hormone secrets also include
things like CJC and there are some
variants on these which can lead to some
insulin resistance but maybe spikes GH a
bit more. I don't know. None of those to
me really seem worth it personally, just
given the effects aren't that great. You
know, if someone can afford it and they
can get a script for it, probably better
to just take pharmagra smatotrope or
omnitrope growth hormone. And you know,
the bodybuilders would take like eight
IUs a day or something crazy like that.
But the in the trials that have been
done with metformin and GH typically
it's people are taking one to two IUs
five nights per week. that will
dramatically increase deep sleep and
probably sleep overall and the effects
on fat loss and just tissue repair
healings and feelings of well-being and
just cognitive function. Anecdotally,
people and subjectively people say like,
"Wow, I just feel so great." This is the
getting up in the morning and be like,
"Wow, my joints feel good." And just
being ready to like go go. It's not
anabolic as much as something like
testosterone, etc. But I'm not telling
people to run out and do GH, but if you
could get a good script, a script for
real GH and take a low dose versus
taking a bunch of like unknown secreted
dog peptides. That seems like a obvious
one for me. Then there's a category of
things like
BPC57, body protection compound 157,
which is a amino acid chain that is in
gastric juice, but it's this isolated
amino acid chain that seems to be the
one that's most popular. And at the same
time, it's the one for which most people
probably are taking it for all the wrong
reasons. I've tried it. I definitely
feel like after a pain or strain, the
recovery is faster, but I can't do the
control experiment because it goes
systemic. So, it's not like you could,
let's say you hurt both biceps. You
could, you can't inject into one bicep
and not the other and assume that it's
just acting locally. It's going to go
systemically. There are capsule forms of
BPC that people claim are just as good.
I don't know. Do you have to inject
locally close to the injury? It seems
that might be helpful. The animal data
on BPC are really impressive. Cartilage
regrowth, fibiberblast migration,
angioenesis, nerve regrowth. It's a
literature I've spent a lot of time
with. There's not a single published
human trial. Where I think the most
interesting use of it perhaps is is I
know someone recently, she wrote to me
and she said that her dog had a spinal
injury and she said, "Does BPC work in
animals?" I go, "Actually, pretty much
all the data are in animals." So if my
dog, god forbid, had an injury, I'd be
willing to give him or her BPC. You have
to work out the appropriate dosage.
>> How would you source that
hypothetically?
>> So you can get it from compoundingies
now. So you need a doctor to write that
script. Depending on your risk
tolerance, you could go to the gray
market for research purposes only. I
wouldn't do that. Peptide Sciences
shuttered their doors, windows,
whatever. They closed a few months back.
They they sense the heat coming on and
they're like, "We're out." They took
their money and they're out. Smart move,
Peptide Sciences. So nowadays, you can
find doctors that will prescribe it.
There's also pentadcaeptide, which is
just a different form of BPC seems to
have same function. It's easier to find.
and getting it from a compounding
pharmacy. Of course, compoundingies vary
in stringency, but is going to be
cleaner than the gray market sourcing of
course, but I have no relationship to
thesearmacies, but for instance, Tailor
Made, Upstate, Revive Pharmacy. These
are kind of the better known and trusted
compoundingies. Compoundingies were
allowed to compound drugs that are still
under patent during shortages and can
compound generic drugs. They'll also
truly compound peptides. You could get
BPC with another one. The TB500, the
so-called Wolverine stack. I don't know.
I've never tried TB500. I keep some BPC
157 in the fridge. If I have a a strain,
I'll
>> Can I hop in for a second? Like the
challenge with so much this stuff is you
can't do the control, right?
>> Cuz I took the Wolverine stack after I
had elbow surgery and I'm like,
>> did it help? I have no idea, frankly. I
have no idea,
>> you know. No, I will say this. I've used
it a few times, very short runs of it.
I'm not interested in using it as a
general recovery tool or every day or I
don't have any gut issues like so people
have used high doses of BPC to resolve
gut issues. That was the original use.
You know in this clinical trial they did
BBC enemas at very high dosages.
>> Sounds like an Austin party [laughter]
>> you know and supposedly I learned this
from Abu Pavlov actually had a side gig.
He was a health influencer. He would
give people gastric juices to try and
resolve ulcers and things like that. And
we know gastric juices contain a number
of beneficial peptides,
>> but I don't recommend
>> How did they down those? How did they
get them in there?
>> How' they down them? And how' they get
them?
>> A glass of gastric juices.
>> I mean, maybe he had a cabinet of people
with the, you know, they're tapping
them. Yeah. So rough. So, you know,
people say, "Should I take BPC?" No, you
shouldn't unless you have an injury or
maybe in that case, you get clean
compounded pharmacy BPC and you inject
it locally or you take it systemically.
You try it, see if it helps. But why
would you take it ongoing? That just
doesn't make any sense to me. It doesn't
make any sense to me, frankly. And
again, you go back to your sort of half
joke at the beginning, you really want
to recover quickly from exercise, take
an IU or two IUs of GH every night
before sleep and you will recover
magnificently well. I mean, in the for
the enhanced games, the swimmer, the
massive lats guy, he recently put his
>> stack out and I think it was 200
milligrams of of cipionate per week. So
that's one cc of standard cypate. That's
a lot. I have to say most people I know
and we can talk about this
>> and I've talked about my cipionate use
and
>> from the beginning and the experiment of
like much much slower. I believe in
micro doing that if at all. He's taking
200 plus I think he's doing two IUs of
growth hormone per night or five nights
per week and he's taking EPO. They can
only take FDA approved drugs. So that's
kind of so it's it's like in
[clears throat]
>> But were they testing at all to verify
if they're FDA approved versus
>> I don't know
>> FDA nonapproved. I mean that would be a
complicated test to run.
>> It's kind of interesting to ask. Was
there any rule breaking in the steroid
Olympics?
>> Yeah. Maybe it was a sink test. You've
heard this, right? Like urine sample and
they just pour in the [laughter]
fast.
>> I mean some of the powerlifters like
Thor were very open about the fact that
they were not allowed to use the things
they would normally use because they
weren't FDA approved. So, it's kind of
interesting. It seemed like they were
kind of running the the middle of the
road, but
>> and that's a lot of juice. I think he
was also, if I'm thinking of the same,
Australian swimmer,
>> I'm not sure, but yeah, he was also
quoted, this is many months before the
actual competition, but he's like, I am
going to juice to the gills. So, it
looks like he almost grew gills cuz his
lats were like, you know, not Yates
size, but he's a very tall guy.
a few Olympics ago, I think it was
wasn't the last one, it was the one
before that, this female runner got
popped for deca and she claimed it came
from a burrito that she ate and the Deca
burrito and you know, I'm a track and
field fan and so are some other folks
around the
>> Dave for people who don't. I'm might be
mispronouncing correctly.
>> Yeah, non aromatizing. Doesn't convert
estrogen as far as we know. People use
it for joint healing and things of that
sort. I've never tried it, but someone
in our studio said this and I think
they're spot on. They hope she used it
because if she didn't and she got nailed
for it from a burrito or some other
source, that sucks because there's a
huge stigma that goes with that. She
gets, you know, she can't compete and
you never really shake that reputation.
>> Yeah.
>> So, my hope is that she actually took it
and got caught as opposed to didn't take
it and got caught for something.
>> I mean, the burrito the [laughter]
burrito alibi is pretty flimsy. Last
time I checked, you can't just nibble on
deca and and have it do much for you.
>> Well, and Canelo Alvarez got popped for
clenbuterol and he claimed it came from
some food he ate in Mexico, you know,
the clen cow, you know, hypothesis.
[laughter]
>> Do you remember back when I think
medafanyl was fair game if it were
prescribed and it was something like the
majority if not all of the finalists in
some of the track and field events were
all diagnosed narcoleptics. They were
all
>> That's right. That's right. What are the
chances that these mutants would all be
narcoleptic?
>> Totally. BPC would be very hard to
detect because your body makes it
naturally. As with the GLPS again, they
stimulate such a massive increase in
action at those receptors that you
probably detect it. Those are the kind
of healing ones, the tissue repair ones.
TB500, BPC. There are others, but those
are the main ones. And then there's the
kind of miscellaneous category things
like epitalin which actually comes from
the pineal which is weird because
there's also a peptide called pinealon
which doesn't come from the pineal.
>> That is confusing.
>> Epalin is thought to allow for
preservation of histone and DNA
structure. It's very vague. There some
decent data on visual repair for animal
models of retinitis pigmentotosa.
maybe more robust circadian setting when
you travel. I may have tried this
recently, a capsule form of Epalon
combined with some sunlight in the
morning for the first two days did seem
to shift my clock more quickly,
>> but I don't know
>> for jet lag.
>> For jet lag maybe, but I'm not going to
do it again cuz I don't know.
>> I don't know if there's a there there.
But I was chatting with this friend of
mine. She's frequent traveler from Japan
to the US. She lives in Japan. She's
constantly going back and forth and
she'll come for just a few days and then
head back. So, the possibility for
getting brutalized is high, just hopping
so many time zones. And she gave me a
tip and I tried it and could be a
placebo, who knows? She was just like,
just fast. She's like, I on the long
flights, I just fast. And I tried that
going to Asia is always a little bit
easier than coming back. [snorts]
>> I was totally fine. I couldn't believe
it cuz I had to do very for short trip
for reasons I won't bore people with.
don't know what the mechanism would be,
but I was like, "Huh,
>> maybe there's something there." I don't
know.
>> Well, we have our central circadian
clock, SCN. Most people have heard of
that now. The eyes connect to it
directly, which is why sunlight and
other forms of light are so efficient at
shifting our clock.
But we have a lot of peripheral clocks,
liver clocks, gut clocks, and those are
usually the last to shift, which is why
a lot of people have kind of feeling
like their stomach is off, digestion is
off when they travel. maybe not
travelers diarrhea, but they just sort
of feel like waking up in the middle of
night, they're hungry, they're on the
the previous location's meal schedule.
Fasting may allow for shifting those
clocks. I mean, it meal times are a very
robust thing in terms of raising our
levels of arousal. You know, there kind
of like you eat every day at noon, like
a couple minutes before you get that
arousal. These they're welltimed
systems.
So, that's not totally surprising.
Pinealon is one I've experimented with
and is very interesting and I have to
say there are very few things that
increase REM sleep. Most things deplete
REM sleep. In fact, if I always joke if
somebody needs a PhD quick and nothing's
working, have them do a study of sleep
and give any drug and it disrupts REM
sleep. You know, I don't study sleep,
but that's a kind of a well-known joke.
>> How do you spell pinealon?
>> P I N E A L O N.
>> Oh, they really want it to be as
confusing as possible. does not come
from the pineal. So the nomenclature
sucks in this area. And we don't even
have names for these different bins,
right? Half baked posttock is like, you
know, what would be really funny
>> to call [laughter] to call the stuff
from the pineal epialon spelled two
different ways, by the way, out there,
epithelal and epital. And pinealon and
then and then swap them, right? Pinealin
comes from the cortex. It's made in the
cortex, neoortex. And I will say there
are a couple things that will increase
REM with no pharmarmacology. you can
heat up your sleeping environment in the
final two hours of your sleep. You'll
get much more REM. Thank you, Matt
Walker, for that trick. It's awesome.
So, cool at the beginning of the night,
cold in the middle of the night, and
warm toward morning. Or throw on a
heated blanket or whatever, a weighted
blanket or some socks and a and a wool
cap as you if you wake up, you know,
about twothirds of the way through your
sleep, use the bathroom. You'll be
surprised how much better your REM is.
The other thing is, and this is a nice
one, if you want to work out late in the
day, you don't want to take caffeine
because you still want to sleep that
night. If you take alpha GPC, you know,
900 migs of of alpha GPC, alpha GPC,
which as you know is increases, it's
like a choline donor, acetyloline, that
system,
you can still sleep that night and it
will increase your REM sleep.
>> And it is true. Remember we said high
cortisol morning, low cortisol at night.
That's the optimal setup that we should
aim for. If you exercise after work,
you're going and you do, let's say, a
highintensity session of any kind, the
resistance training we were talking
about earlier, for instance, you will
triple or quadruple your cortisol
levels. I should also earmark that as
all this stuff online, which seems
mainly directed towards women, like, oh,
cold showers and baths, ice baths, are
going to spike your cortisol. That's
terrible. The increase in cortisol from
deliberate cold exposure is trivial
compared to what working out with
weights will do. So late day cortisol
spikes are no problem if it comes up and
down, but you also wouldn't want to take
caffeine on top of that and disrupt your
sleep. So if you have a late day workout
and you need a bit of a stimulant, alpha
GPC is a good tool and you'll likely get
more REM sleep.
>> So it's a nice one. And then pinealon
I will use every once in a while.
>> For what reason?
>> You get three hours of REM if you're me.
>> Three hours. And it doesn't disrupt your
slowwave deep sleep. It is wild. And
here's the cool part. It works that
night and it seems to work all the
nights after carryover.
>> There's carryover and it seems the
hypothesis based on the animal data is
that it can help quote unquote
regenerate the pineal, which is a
dangerous term because you don't want
cells proliferating either.
>> Yeah.
>> So, who knows what it's doing, but I'll
use it every once in a while.
>> Always a good place to start.
>> Now, Abood likes it in the daytime.
He'll take it in the daytime. People use
it for cognitive enhancement. He claims
there's a founder of a major company
that has all his employees on it for
daytime work. I know someone that takes
it during the daytime because they're
they're uh he's a songwriter, very
talented songwriter and he likes the
kind of hypnotic state it puts him in.
I'm interested in sleeping at night and
being alert during the day.
>> Great tool for occasional use.
>> Is that subcutaneous injection or what
is that?
>> They also have oral forms. I've only
tried the subcutaneous injection and you
do need to find a doctor that can
prescribe it, get it from a compounding
pharmacy. I think pinealon is a very
interesting compound and I've been
monitoring my blood work the whole time
doing this. So tried smearellin stopped
using I've never used a GLP. I'm kind of
curious because a lot of people are
talking about lowd dose tzepide or
reatutide like a tenth of the prescribed
dose for not just weight loss but for
just cognitive well-being but
>> yeah neuroprotective effects
>> neuroprotective effects maybe other
things.
>> Yeah I'm interested in that stuff. I
mean I'm so curious and maybe there's
literature out I haven't read it, but if
the mechanism of action is separate from
the
metabolic effects, right?
>> Right.
>> Because if you take someone who has
insulin resistance or is on the path to
insulin resistance and you correct for
that, then that in and of itself on some
>> level should be neuroprotective, right?
Especially if you're looking at vascular
dementia or
>> any number of things. So glaucoma,
there's some interesting data that
tepatide may reduce eye pressure. So
that's interesting.
BPC57 has this asterisk next to it. It
will cause angioenesis. So people are
saying you don't want to vascularize a
tumor obviously
accelerate cancers that kind of thing.
You don't want to supply more blood
nutrients to a tumor. It'll gobble them
up and grow. But it is not mutagenic. So
it's not carcinogenic mutagenic per se.
And that's important. Here's something
interesting too. There's a kind of
sociology behind all of these. There are
a couple more we can touch on, but the
GLPS, the prescription GLPs
and the massive growth of that area
>> is guilty of making the general public
comfortable with injections.
>> So, you know, it's kind of interesting.
The battles online are between Yeah. So,
you know, it's like you created this
problem. You know, most people don't
talk about this, but the traditional
media and medicine like to couch the
peptide thing is a bunch of gym bros.
Mm- [clears throat]
massive market in women.
>> Sure,
>> most people taking these peptides are
not gymgoing guys. It's women who want
to take a lowd dose reetta, but rea is
not out yet. or they want to take
lowdoseptide
cocktailed with NAD with some GHKU
copper or GHK copper which is for
there's some studies that show that in
combination with red light therapy or
some sun exposure just enough might
remove wrinkles. The biggest market is
women and I'm not like trying to defend
the bro science guy but it's kind of
funny that the target has been like
these guys on X who are selling cup
ties. That's not where to place an
>> easier target. There's also this very
interesting sociology around kind of
nattier or not stuff and
>> what the hell does that mean?
>> Yeah, exactly. I mean, if someone takes
GLPS, are they now
>> natural? Yeah. And you know, for men,
that's kind of the thing like does
someone get called out or not? My
recommendation, this is what I've always
done is always just talk about
everything you've taken or are taking or
not taking.
>> Well, also, can I pause for a second
just to say I I think I'm getting the
name of the doc right. bigger, stronger,
faster, such as Mark Bell and Chris
Bell, I think it was, who directed and
made the film. Great film to watch. It's
older,
>> but at some point they're talking about
this. And they put up, I want to say
it's a fourpoint quadrant, I mean, by
definition. And they're like, "Okay, so
you can inject EPO, right, to increase
red blood cell count and like oxygen
carry capacity." Okay. And they're like,
"Or you can live at altitude, right? Or
you can have a
altitude simulation tent
>> or and they're like are any of these
natural
>> right you get an infusion of your own
blood testosterone cipionate will
increase red blood cell count and people
don't talk about that was it's not EPO
like but you certainly
>> cardio gets better so even without the
addition of muscle recovery gets better
>> I'll tell you I mean personally and I've
written about this which is funny just
to maybe air grievance right I remember
like I talked at length in the 4-hour
body about postsurgical anabolic use and
then like online it's like Tim Ferrris
admits and I'm like admit I [__]
wrote about it at length totally just
the wording is such a weasel word I
admitted
>> oh yeah somehow even though 5 years ago
I said oh yeah like I decided to run an
experiment where I'm tried to sipionate
with hCG you know keep keep sperm
production online and just low dose and
just see what's the minimal effective
dose
>> I'm not competing in any sports like I
don't think it makes that big of a
difference except in terms of recovery.
I didn't change my training before after
I went off and on again like okay so
that's within the male community in
women and peptides. There's this other
piece which is like who's getting
plastic surgery and who's not. Nowadays
the dermatologists certainly in Los
Angeles but in Northern California too
recommend some amount of laser
resurfacing to reduce cancer risk but it
also reduces wrinkles. So you know like
what are people doing? None of it is
particularly natural. I think for
competitive sports is where it becomes
an important issue. But I think that
the pharma grade JLP world made sticking
little tiny needles 31 gauge or 30 gauge
needles into one's skin to inject
something just kind of like okay no
biggie. And I'll tell you the first
person to sell pharmagra maybe
compounded pharmacy
peptide pens where you just dial it in.
It's not a syringe. People are much more
comfortable with pens than they are with
syringes. They're going to make a
killing. So then there are a bunch of
other things like melanotan makes people
tan but it can make you way too tan. Can
cause priisism like permanent erection
which dangerously long erection greatly
increase libido. But keep in mind vi is
a FDA approved drug for female
hyposexuality.
>> Lowers orgasmic threshold, stimulates
libido.
It also works in men. I've never tried
it, but it also works in men.
>> Not sure most men want.
>> And I asked Yeah. So I asked someone at
Stanford who's in the department
department of urology. Actually, there
are a lot of interesting drugs that are
pro libbido
>> for men, but they'll never get marketed
because the idea of more men wanting
more sex is just not something that
society seems to want.
>> Yeah. Although with the shift in kind of
self-hatred and one could argue kind of
diminished, you know, aspects of mental
and physical health and maybe some
people would really benefit from it. But
melanotan is yet another example. And
then my view on the peptides thing is
this. You do you, whoever you are. You
decide what your risk thresholds are,
but just be logical about it. Why would
you take BPC if you don't have an
injury? It's not going to accelerate
your recovery that much. Certainly not
as much as getting better sleep. So
maybe you would think oh pinealon but
get your relationship to light correct
get your relationship to caffeine
correct and I have to say like I've
gotten great benefit from the mag 3 and8
epigenine theonine stack I don't think
you need pinealon until you've tried
everything else and then maybe try a
supplement stack or even just one of
those things and then if you still need
it then pinealon makes sense but just
leaping to pineal doesn't make sense
given how little data there are but
there are some interesting drugs out
there too like the doras.
>> I'm taking balsamra.
>> Okay.
>> Mostly because of the Alzheimer's that
runs in in my family. Super prevalent.
>> Does it help your sleep?
>> It does. I can end up feeling a bit
groggy in the morning, but you could
explain. I mean, I ended up, you know,
chatting with, as probably you did at
some point, Matt Walker about this, very
knowledgeable. It's still preliminary,
but pretty interesting mechanistically
>> in terms of clearance of various goodies
that you do not want in your brain, at
least as far as we know now. So yeah,
we'll see. It does help with sleep. The
daytime sort of morning groggginess can
be a bit of a hassle. So I've been
cycling on and off of it.
>> I tried Quivic once, which is one of the
Doras.
>> I got zombie sleep. I woke up in the
same position I fell asleep in. I didn't
feel rested even though I had slept
through the night.
>> I've just not gone to prescription tools
for it. But some people seem to like
prescription tools. I think incidentally
there's a really nice paper published in
proceedings of the National Academy of
Sciences USA showing that short
meditations can increase glimpmphatic
clearance in the daytime. This is very
interesting. I think
>> that's cool.
>> Yeah, very cool. Like when you go into
this meditative state, long exhales
focusing on breathing you know
meditation more clearance of waste
products on the brain during the
meditation and in sleep that night it
seems increased which is really
interesting. So many people care about
their nighttime HRV. Best way to
increase nighttime HRV, as long as you
don't have apnea or some other issue, is
to do some exhale emphasized breathing
practice during the day. Even just a few
deliberate exhales during the day can
increase nighttime HRV. So there seems
to be this daytime nighttime
relationship that's pretty cool.
>> Interestingly, something for future
research, but I've seen HRV changes post
TMS.
>> Oh, interesting. Pretty pretty
fascinating to check out. Yeah,
>> post TMS. Sorry, for a moment I heard TM
because I was like I think I think Tim
Ferrris TM I think you know.
>> Yeah. Well, probably both, right? The
glimpmphatic stuff also is very
intertwined with a lot of psychedelic
science. Not to bring us back to that,
but the glimpmphatic clearance is really
>> fascinating. So, I'd love to check out
that.
>> We'll put it in the show notes. So, I'll
get that from you.
>> Yeah, very cool paper. The author sent
it to me before it came out and I think
it's just a really important finding. I
go into a little bit in my book, but it
was a late it was a recent finding, so
didn't have time to go into it too much.
But if ever you needed another incentive
to meditate for a few minutes, that's
one. For the peptide thing, you know,
it's funny. I I feel like people feel
safe enough to try them because they're
enough like supplements, enough like
drugs that they feel comfortable doing
it. And you know, cipionate sounds so
scary. It's like, okay, or GH sounds so
scary. But there's a lot more data
and they're pharmarmacra and
small dosages are always going to be
better than big dosages. And the
fertility thing on anything that
increases testosterone is very real.
They've talked about inhalants and oral
forms that don't disrupt fertility, but
anyone that wants to maintain fertility
is going to have to take hcg while
taking that, right?
>> Yeah. Or postcycle therapy with clomid
or something. But yeah.
>> Yeah. So, I think that the peptide thing
is very interesting. I I get excited
anytime the general public is thinking
about biology and I love Abud's
framework of people are now mining the
body for medicines and maybe that's why
people feel
like you'll see these criticisms and and
they're understandable like oh all these
people that wouldn't take a prescription
drug will take these peptides. I think
that when people hear that something's
of the body, even if it's a synthetic
form of something of the body, they're
more likely to take it.
>> Mhm.
>> And I can't quite relate to that
psychology, but I sort of get it. I sort
of get it. It's not some stardust thing.
At the same time, you're not going to
see huge effects from any of these
things except perhaps pinealon, and
they're still that's still anecdotal and
the GLPS from Red True Tide. Those have
really robust effects. everything else.
BBC can have its potential role in
healing for some people, but there are
no trials. And by the way, no one's
going to do a trial and no one's going
to do it properly. I keep hearing, oh,
there's going to be a hamstring injury
trial, there's going to be no one wants
to put the time and effort and having
run a clinical trial and having done
experiments in pre-clinical animal
format for lunch, it's a lot of work to
do properly. You need to know what the
end points are.
>> It's expensive. Who's going to pay for
it? Also,
>> right? And I just don't see it
happening. I think people are just going
to take the stuff. I think the big win
for someone out there, someone with an
entrepreneurial spirit is going to be
Americanmade
clean peptides with verified sourcing
and all that so people can trust what
they're what they're getting.
>> Yeah, I've seen, as you might imagine,
like a thousand different startups
trying to produce their own peptides or
whatever it might be. The only one I
don't think I can talk about it yet, but
the only one I backed is actually going
to be verifying supply chain and all of
that. It's just a stamp of this is what
it says it is on the box basically.
>> And it's interesting that unlike
anabolic steroids which in the 80s and
in the '9s and to some extent still
today but really in the 80s and 90s
where there were these kind of
outrageous adverse events, right? You
know, people committing murders, massive
acne, dying, you know, brain tumors and
all which was the consequence of
probably a bunch of things, GH and
steroids. To my knowledge, there has not
been
a reported adverse event that can be
tacked back to one of these non-FDA
approved
>> peptides. And I'm not saying that means
they're safe, but it's interesting that
there are a lot of women taking them.
There are a lot of men taking them, but
there are a lot of women taking GHK
copper in cream form or injectable form
>> if they're having terrible adverse well
adverse terrible that's redundant
adverse events.
>> They're not reporting.
>> This is super important. I mean, I think
there's a book called Bad Science by Ben
Goldacaker who's an MD from the UK.
There are a number of chapters that are
not relevant to a US audience, but it's
a helpful book for teaching yourself to
think in a structured way, right,
scientifically about medicine.
>> And I think what you said is really
important in the sense that well, let me
use an analogy. Let's say we've got
Honda Civic, tons of Honda Civics, man,
they've been around a long time. Or just
to say cars, okay, you got all this data
on all these horrible accidents. You've
got vehicular manslaughter. You've got
all this stuff, right? [snorts] Pretty
bad report card, right? Lots of deaths.
And then you're like, "But we've got
this brand new Tron motorcycle, fresh
off the press, right? No documented
deaths, therefore it must be safe." And
you're like, "Wait a second." Yep.
>> That thing has not had a lot of mileage
on it. Only one person has used it. And
I'm using a bit of an exaggerated
example because, you know, this absence
of evidence does not equal evidence of
absence, right? And this is true also
again not to sound like a broken record
but whether it's whether it is gray
market rea or
DIY for research purposes only peptide
use or psychedelics which still remain
illegal in most places. There's no real
reporting mechanism,
>> right? It's like if you have a doctor
and they prescribe you something and
they ask you how's it going and you're
like I'm growing horns, got hemorrhoids,
whatever the side effects might be. I'm
feeling really anxious. There is some
means by which
>> the feedback makes it back into the
system,
>> right? And certainly with clinical
trials and so on, you would hope that to
be the case. So for me, it's like when
I'm looking at these things, I'm like,
"All right, well, they might be great,
>> but I feel some degree of reassurance. I
haven't taken any anabolics in forever.
Maybe if I were trying to have six kids,
I'd be like, "Yeah, let's do HCG," which
does seem to have a pretty, for me, at
least profound impact on libido, which
is sometimes nice. HCG? Oh yeah,
>> that's probably due to the fact just a
opportunity to throw in perhaps
something useful is
>> the old lore was guys want high
testosterone, low estrogen. You want
your estrogen as high as you can without
getting side effects.
>> Yeah.
>> For libido purposes, for endothelial
health, brain health cardrotective
protective
>> bone density. guys that quash their they
take temoxifen or
an estastriol to quash their estrogen
levels that is a mistake. They often
find that they have reduced libido. They
sort of dry out so to speak. They get
more vulnerability to injuries. Hardly
anybody nowadays does testosterone
replacement therapy with an astrol.
Almost every person goes like I just
feel better when I don't take it. Now
guys are getting like gyno and like all
sorts of things. They need to be
careful. But for brain health, for
libido, for all those things, hCG is
going to increase both testosterone and
estrogen. And even for just sort of skin
vitality, look, you know, not something
men talk about too often, but if
testosterone is too high and estrogen's
low, skin doesn't look good. [laughter]
>> It It just doesn't look good. It's It's
the chicken skin. It's like the thin
chicken skin thing.
>> Yeah. I mean, heavy anabolic users, not
known for their pretty skin.
>> Not known for their pretty skin. And I
think it's just really interesting that
the peptide thing is all the rage
to my knowledge. Not a lot of adverse
events that can be separated out from,
you know, I always hear like infected
injection site. Okay. So, use an alcohol
swab, pin yourself carefully. Don't
>> I just want to double click on that for
a second because when people get
cavalier with injections, it's like
speaking to someone who from a
professional ended up getting a staff
infection in the elbow.
>> Oh, yeah. That's right. Take your
hygiene seriously when it comes to
injections. Right.
>> I'm just looking.
>> Don't run and gun and like behind the
dumpster at the Denny's with no alcohol
swab. Don't do that.
>> Yeah. Don't do that. Don't reuse
needles. Don't dip back into the vial
with a needle cuz you didn't get enough
cuz it can contaminate the vial. Like
use good good practices. But, you know,
a lot of people think that moving to
creams or to capsules is going to sell
more peptides. Very interesting
observation I think is that people want
the injectables. It feels more real.
>> Capsules feel more like supplements
which are a mixed bag.
>> It's interesting, right? If I told you,
okay, BPC and capsule form, same as
injectable, you know, yeah, but if I
inject it, the injury site, it just kind
of feels like more is going on. This is
where placebo effect may actually be
real. Or it may be that the capsule
forms are not as as good. Well, also I
mean we're getting in the weeds here,
but just because something is oral also
doesn't mean it's safer than injectable,
right? Because you look at like anadrol
50 versus injectable test cipionate.
It's like if you're smashing your liver,
>> right,
>> like you can do a lot of damage.
>> Oh, absolutely. I don't think people
should run around doing anabolics by all
means. I certainly the number of guys in
their like 20s, 30s, and even 40s that
think that they need it, it's not
necessarily. So, one thing that I think
would be wonderful, I'm very excited
about this, but it would be wonderful
for the overall field, but for
supplementation in particular, you know,
blood work has gotten relatively
inexpensive now. A number of companies,
they brought the cost of blood testing
way down. People are now comfortable
having someone take their blood and
sending them their blood work. So,
there's a sociology to this. There's a
shift.
Wouldn't it be wonderful to get your
blood work done? And then I envision
like a 3D printed blister pack with your
morning and your afternoon or your
morning and nighttime supplements that
are tailored to your blood work. 3
months later you take you do your blood
work again and you get to see whether or
not markers are moving into range better
>> update the 3D printing ideally pharma
grade. That's how supplementation should
be done. And I'm excited for that
possibility. And that's much more my
focus now
>> at least in terms of this kind of stuff.
a lot of different FOSI but in terms of
injectables and pills and things like
that then thinking about what's
happening with peptides because the
legislation is changing constantly you
know next administration could come in
whoever that happens to be it could all
get revamped it's not a wild west but
it's just not a well- definfined field
yet
>> oh I think it's pretty wild west just my
two cents I'm very conservative with
this stuff these days maybe I'm just
getting old and boring I don't know I
think as I've gotten older I have just
whether it's through the literature or
maybe being on the receiving ends of a
lot of anecdotal reports of adverse
events for various things. I'm just
like, man, there's such a typical lack
of reporting
>> in wide population adverse events. Yeah.
>> That I'm like, man,
>> you just got to measure twice and cut
once.
And if I can pick something that has 50
or 100 years of research where I know
with some certainty what the adverse
events are and the probability of those
adverse events versus the latest and
greatest thing where it's like yeah fly
down to Honduras and have this gene
therapy [laughter]
and hope it goes well. I'm like ah the
gene therapy thing is not ready in my
opinion. You know, we have a colleague
in the health field who got an injection
of stem cells into his spine and ended
up with pretty with paralysis and almost
died. Yeah. Terrible.
>> And grateful to the neurosurgeons at
UCSF. Shout out to chair of neurosurgery
Eddie Chang who didn't do the surgery,
but one of his surgeons in his
department did. And that injected with
stem cells person is now mobile and
healthy and strong. But it was a really
close call. I know I actually got a call
during the surgery about how it was
going. There was this was a really good
example of how even with attempted best
practices and stem cell injections,
there's always the potential for local
infection and rejection. Well, let me
give you one more. Not to be like the
old guy who can't deal with the young
whipper snappers, but well, the goal
nowadays is to be the old guy. Well,
here's the thing. Also, there's
mechanical risk in the sense that I've
had stem cell injections from like the
most vetted at every step of the process
stem cells
and from young donors. I won't go into
all the details, but like very very well
vetted and involving us doctors. And the
doctor happened to have well I don't
know if he was busy preoccupied
distracted but a little sloppy technique
on trying to give me stem cells around
the medial collateral ligament and
injected my fat pad in the knee and made
a bunch of structural damage and my knee
was [__] and like still like this is a
year or two later have residual pain in
my knee that is from physical damage
with the needle. So it's like depending
on what you're doing, if it's
intraarticular or you're getting in
there, [snorts]
>> it's not a foregone conclusion that it's
going to be a smooth ride. And this is
someone with thousands of injections,
like they have the mileage. And this is,
as far as I can tell, talking to other
orthos and people who do similar
injections, like it's a routine
injection. The path of injection is very
well established.
>> Wow.
>> Nonetheless, off day, smash, blew up to
the size of volleyball the next day. Oh,
Helen Blau's lab at Stanford School of
Medicine had a beautiful paper where
they had mouse data and human data
inhibiting a specific molecule. I don't
recall which and you could regrow
cartilage in the knee that's clearly
headed off to clinical trials and
pharma, but the effects that were
demonstrated were incredible. There's an
active inhibitor of cartilage regrowth,
and apparently you can inhibit the
inhibitor and bring back cartilage.
Wouldn't that be wonderful? again mining
the body for its own quote unquote
medicines. I mean none of this stuff was
supposed to happen naturally and so
we've been kind of pushing and proddding
from the outside taking things plant
derivatives that mimic neurotransmitters
you know psilocybin is just one example
but all these drug companies biorpect
from plants learned that from Chris
Mccertie the expert onratom and it's
cool it's really cool I think medicine's
on the fast track and I'm super excited
about AI as a tool for self-directed
medical exploration not necessarily for
you know deciding which peptides to take
but maybe
but in terms of people trying to figure
out like hey am I taking anything that
might make my autoimmune condition worse
you know I have a friend he's got MS and
takes a bunch of things eats a bunch of
things you know turns out certain forms
of mustard can flare up MS you know not
everybody but
>> AI can look at your food intake look at
your habits look at supplementation
make recommendations and that's super
powerful and I just feel like AI is
going to be an incredible medical tool
not just in terms of its ability to
outperform physicians or aid physicians
but for people to really understand
their blood work and understand the
trajectories of their sleep scores and
all this stuff like I'm very very
excited then again I'm born and raised
in Silicon Valley so I'm not thinking
about the dystopian view of AI robots
you know robots taking over. I'm
thinking about people having more
information and agency.
>> For me right now, the most interesting
application of the LLM is for health
purposes. I mean, it's remarkable. I
have friends who have the best doctors
you can imagine, the most expensive
folks you can conceive of. And they they
have still caught stuff because no one's
going to take your health as seriously
as you are. Nor will even if they take
it seriously, will they have the time
that you will dedicate to it. and
they've uploaded their genomes, added in
the various bits and bobs from wearables
and taken PDFs of labs and thrown them
in and found very very
material insights that had not surfaced
earlier in decades.
>> It's not one person. It's not two
people. This is at least four or five
people I can think of who have all the
means, all the time, all the interest.
And yet it took these LLMs as a data
dump and the ability of those LLMs to
mine everything and to look for
interrelated components to surface these
in their cases actionable insights and
it's early. This is top of the first,
right? It's early for these things. So
they're just going to get better.
>> It is just going to get better. And one
thing that Eddie Chang, this incredible
neurosurgeon who studies speech and
language at UCSF, Again, I've known him
since I was seven and he's just this
phenom.
He pointed out to me, he's like, you
know, all the
LLMs, they're all trained on the
internet. Like right now, AI is trained
on the internet. It's not like trained
on human brain activity. The next big
step is recording your brain activity
non-invasively ideally. And building
some AI tools from your brain activity,
like what's going on when you're in your
most focused mode? What does that look
like? What does it look like if you take
uh you know 100 milligrams of a given
stimulant? What's your brain activity
look like? Are there ways that you could
modify your pharmacology and behavior
and sleep and all that to really get
your brain activity working the way you
want? And so the real holy grail of AI,
he tells me, is AI built on neural
activity, not based on the internet,
which is just it's the output of our
neural activity. Of course, that
occurred to me, but it hadn't occurred
to me in that form. Mhm.
>> And he and others are developing these
ways of reading from the nervous system.
You know that right now you mentioned
wearables.
It's like whether it's a whoop or it's
an aura, it's your h sleep, it's
measuring heart rate and body motion
mainly. Accelerometers, HRV. By the way,
the HRV is the reflection of how often
that descending branch of the Vegas
slows your heart rate down. That's what
it is. So every time you, you know,
you're increasing HRV, you're slowing
your heart rate down. It's just that's
the veagal reflection in your Whoop
score in your sleep score from your
aura. The HRV is that while that's
great, that's not a direct readout of
your autonomic nervous system. That's
heart rate. Okay. Well, that's a start.
But what about direct read of the
autonomic nervous system? Oo.
>> Mhm.
>> What about a little sticker that can
record non-invasively the number of
nerve impulses traveling up a branch of
the Vegas? A lot of them travel really
superficially behind the ears.
What about a non-invasive brain
stimulator that looks like a baseball
cap? You know, a few years ago, there
were things like Halo, which were
designed to ramp up neural activity,
accelerate plasticity. I don't know how
good or bad the data were, but it didn't
really stick to be honest.
writing to the nervous system, writing
to the body. That's where it's at. And I
think everyone who's thinking about AI
seems to also be thinking about that.
The not so well-kept secret among the
big AI companies. If you notice, like a
lot of them are starting to acquire
biotech companies. There's an interest
in biotech. I don't think it's about
advanced search engines
per se. I think it's about how are we
going to control our own neural activity
and brain states and bodily states. I'm
certain that's where it's all headed.
So, what's going to be the first thing
to break through? There have been a
number of things that have, you know,
commercial veagal stimulators to try and
calm people down. They haven't worked
that well. I'm going to piss some people
off there, but like they're kind of weak
songs.
>> Most of them are garbage. They don't
they don't actually stimulate the Vegas
nerve. Most of them
>> or do it specifically enough or robustly
enough. Totally agree. I think a really
interesting place is if we look at
sleep. sleep states and measuring sleep
states has gotten really good even with
just heart rate and body motion and now
like with something like eight sleep
using AI it's making temperature
adjustments for you this would be
amazing to have for waking states like
let's just say during the course of this
conversation the room was dynamically
changing in temperature the seat was
changing a little bit I don't know maybe
my Vegas was being stimulated a little
bit just to keep me in whatever zone was
optimal for this it would just figure it
out AI would just figure it out I think
that The big first use of writing to the
nervous system is going to be for sleep.
And I'll just give you three examples.
First are is a study where they looked
at a rocking of a bed, a mechanical slow
rocking of a bed and how that improves
sleep. And it's remarkable how much it
accelerates the transition into sleep,
how deep people's sleep gets, etc. They
also did that study how fast people need
to walk back and forth while rocking
their baby. Turns out a certain number
of paces. There's a paper I can send you
the reference and sell reports. Turns
out parents figure out the ideal pace
and I forget how many like hertz it is,
you know, but it very closely mimics
what the the bedrocking needs to be. So
you go, okay, what is all this like?
Okay, we were born in water. No. Yeah,
that's not what it's about. That's from
a sound ceremony. No disrespect to the
sound ceremony. It's been to some pretty
cool sound ceremonies. The thing about
this is in order to fall asleep, you
need to forget your body position. huge
important step in falling asleep. And it
turns out that there's a way to do this.
There's this crazy eye movement thing
that was published in Reader's Digest
some time ago and went kind of viral
even though viral wasn't around then.
>> Mhm.
>> Where they told people to make
themselves fall asleep by closing their
eyes and slowly moving their eyes to one
side, then the other side, then
counterclockwise, then clockwise, then
kind of crossing their eyes and looking
at their nose, and then doing a long
exhale. What in the world is this? I've
tried this. Yes, you generally find
yourself waking up the next morning.
It's wild. But the really cool thing
happened when there a couple guys at MIT
reached out and they're like, "Hey,
we've got this sleep mask. We'd love for
you to try it. It measures REM directly
by looking at eye movements and it can
induce sleep in under six minutes." How?
They're like, "Oh, it creates with
stimulation behind the ears. It can
stimulate eye movements and you forget
your body position, you fall asleep.
It's affecting the vestibular system,
>> right? So the eyes are linked to the
vestibular system through to control
retinal slip. There's this whole thing
like, you know, like pitch, yaw, and
roll. As you move through space, you
need to stabilize images in the retina.
So your cerebellum and your vestibular
ocular pathways. There's a couple
synapses in between. I'm very familiar
with this because this is like what my
lab used to work on for a significant
portion of time. We're like, Victor, I
figure out which retinal cells and which
targets in the brain stem and on and on.
Anyway, fauculus of the cerebellum. This
eye mask is really cool. You put it on.
I have no relationship to this company.
I think they sort of approached me, but
I didn't do anything with them. But I
think it's just really, really cool. You
put the eye mask on and you feel a
little twitch behind your ear. You
adjust it down so you don't feel it
anymore. And you, what's wild is your
eyes just start moving.
>> I feel like that would keep me up. It
does. I guess maybe you get used to it
after a night or two.
>> It makes you feel very sleepy. So,
there's also a relationship between
certain eye movements and overall
arousal state. Now, this stuff, I don't
want to call it crude, but this is the
first fora into writing to the nervous
system to induce a brain state. And what
I love about it is it's so objective.
Like, if you try this thing, again, I'm
not selling this thing, but if you were
to try this thing, you're like, this
didn't really help me. You know, I want
my money back guarantee. You're good.
Whereas a lot of the stuff for
plasticity, for focus, it's kind of
subjective.
>> Yeah.
>> And it's subject to the placebo effect.
So I think sleep have been the first
place where reading from the nervous
system has been really prominent with
auras and whoops and eight sleeps and
things of that sort. I think sleep is
also going to be the place where writing
to the nervous system is going to happen
first.
>> Let's talk about writing in a different
way. You are a podcast native and yet
the author of the upcoming book
protocols an operating manual for the
human body. What is the structure of the
book? You alluded to the seven
minibooks. What what should people
expect in the book?
>> So, an introduction that defines how to
use the book. I've always liked those.
How to use this book and it my backstory
and
the sort of energetic drive, the
spiritual drive behind wanting to do a
book that teaches science and is about
health and well-being and performance.
People can skip it or they can read it.
Doesn't really matter to me. The first
chapter is all about sleep. So you're
going to learn the science of sleep and
you'll learn the various protocols from
most important most effective to still
effective but lesser important protocols
for sleep and most importantly why they
work based on the science you just
learned. Then a chapter on exercise
defines the program we talked about.
Also a section on mobility on a lot of
people talked about walking and steps
but kind of really identifies what's
needed there what the science actually
says. a section on cardiovascular
exercise and how to structure that.
Again, the goal being yes, I think that
program will work exceptionally well for
anybody. But the principles to fall out
of it are not you need to do this class
or that class. Once a week, get your
heart rate as close to maxed out as you
can in a controlled safe way. Once a
week do this, okay? And why and what the
benefits are, what the science says. The
part about resistance training was also
a lot of fun to really dig into the now
excellent science that's been done about
what actually triggers hypertrophy and
strength. Turns out you can do anywhere
from five to 30 repetitions as long as
you take them to failure and still get
the same hypertrophy results. But then
you have to be practical. Step back and
go like, am I going to do 30 reps of
bicep curls? Maybe. But I'm going to do
30 reps of squats to failure. Well,
those first 20,
>> if you haven't tried that, have fun.
>> Yeah, exactly. And it's very hard to
keep perfect form with high repetitions.
It's actually easier to do with moderate
to heavy weights. Heavy for the
individual that is. Third chapter is
about stress and stress mitigation. That
was a fun one cuz that's was an active
area of my lab for a long time. The next
chapter is about light.
>> Talking about how LEDs are not
necessarily a problem. can't get
incandescent anymore. But if you're not
getting enough longwavelength light, how
that's problematic for a number of
things related to mitochondrial health,
retinal health.
>> Is longwave light a decent way to think
of natural light or
>> Yes. So the sun is full spectrum.
Everything from UV all the way up to
red, near infrared and infrared, the
heat from the sun being infrared. When
the sun is low in the sky, you're going
to glean more of the long wavelength
light and less UV because of something
called relay scattering. That's why the
sun appears more yellow or orange when
it's low in the sky. The goal really is
to get as much long wavelength light.
It's a high quality protein of light
without getting too much UV. You need
some UV. The challenge is in the middle
of the day when the sun is overhead.
You're going to get full spectrum light,
but you're going to get too much. Many
people get too much UV. Now, this is
controversial. People are like, oh, you
know, the more sunlight you get, the
longer you live. Time of day that you
get your sunlight is important, not just
for setting of circadian clocks, but for
other things. Because I also talk about
how long wavelength light can actually
penetrate through your a t-shirt like
yours go all the way through your body.
>> And because long wavelength light is
absorbed by water, it actually is
absorbed in the portions of your cells
that enhance movement on the electron
chain
in mitochondria.
>> Mhm.
>> This notion that we are batteries is
kind of true. If you ever go snorkeling,
you'll notice after about 10 ft or so,
the the red fish disappear.
>> They didn't disappear, right? The red
was absorbed in the top meters of water
and actually a lot of animals and and
fish will come up to the surface because
there's a lot of interesting nutrients
happening. Long wavelength light bounces
off greenery. If you were to put
infrared goggles on during the daytime,
you just the greenery is just reflecting
long wavelength light like crazy, which
is weird because it's green, which means
it should be absorbing the long
wavelength light. I talk a little bit
about light and electromagnetic energy
in a way that should be accessible to
people. So that chapter was like a like
there was so much fun and I haven't
thought about the sun that way in a long
time.
But the goal is for people to understand
the difference between red light therapy
if you're under a lot of, you know, LED
lights or in front of screens at night,
why it's important to try and get some
sunlight during the day to offset some
of that. Not just because of the sleep
effects, but what you don't want is a
lot of shortwave LED light without
longwavelength light in your 24-hour
cycle
>> or daylight daylight cycle can lead to
myopia, lengthening the eyeball, which
means the image focuses to the front of
the retina. So, why people wear
corrective lenses and a few other things
about the relationship between light on
the skin and hormone production and why
that's helpful and longevity.
Okay, that's five. Great. Then chapter
six is about neuroplasticity learning
and ways to increase alertness. And I go
through it all all the behavioral tools,
the pharmarmacology. I talk about
aderall senosi. I talk about how
throughout history people have since
they discovered it have found ways to
get caffeine and nicotine into their
system. They will not quit doing this. I
talked about the relative benefits and
risks of these different things,
delivery mechanisms. And I talk about
the real science of neuroplasticity. And
that of course is, you know, an old love
of mine and wheelhouse of mine. So to
really talk about what it takes to do, I
call them learning belts, like if you're
going to sit down and do something hard.
I mean, I think that's what the writing
of the book was for me is the way I
described it is the need to experience
that internal friction and how important
that is, not just for the relief of when
it's over, but how important that is for
brain longevity. And I really hope
people will take it upon themselves to
learn something new. I know you this was
a active area for you, you know,
learning tango, learning kickboxing,
learning so many things to cook and just
the incredible value of that for life
enrichment, but also for brain health
and longevity.
>> For sure. Even multilingualism is
correlated, to be clear, correlated to
longer health span.
>> There's some really interesting stuff
out there. So yeah, keep learning.
>> There's an Instagram page. I'll find it.
I discovered it in the wee hours of
travel. I got to find this kid's name.
And
all he does is he takes three days to
learn things from complete beginner to
extreme performer of like one thing like
the hardest clarinet song and you see
him start at the beginning. He's all
excuse [snorts] me I'm spitting
everywhere. But that's what he did too.
And then at the end he's like playing
this clarinet. He's like yes. Or can he
do like juggling a soccer ball? Can you
do that for like a 100 kicks and then
kick it into the b like and like swish
it? He just shows how if you just
completely pour yourself into things,
you can learn this stuff. But the range
of things that he's doing is like
totally outrageous. And he's not I don't
know him, but if he had faked one of
them, I might you might be able to
detect it. I don't think he did, but
he's just music, sport, all sorts of
like cool cool stuff.
>> Yeah, give us the handle.
>> Yeah, I'll find it. Really really cool.
This kid is so he's got that energy. It
reminds me a lot of of your experiments
in neuroplasticity. and you're like, I'm
going to play a drum solo in front of a
ton of people. Like, put the pressure
on. And it's just so cool. And then the
last chapter, I had a hard time titling
because it's not about relationships.
I thought about calling it relationship
to self. It's really about personal
development, like how to
structure all the information that's out
there. And it it has a number of things.
has a section on how to navigate grief
based on the science and practices of
navigating grief which those practices
just even the understanding of what
grief is. This remapping of our
understanding of what's actionable and
what's not. It really is an activation
of the reward circuitry that can't be
fulfilled.
>> It's like as if I was dying of thirst
and I'm trying to reach for this and I
can't get it. That's what grief really
is.
>> It's the occasionally I'll get a call
from my graduate adviser who passed I
was very close with from her daughter.
She uses her phone number and it still
comes up as her mom's name. And there's
this moment where I'm like and I'm like,
"Oh." And you feel this sink.
>> I love talking to her daughter. She
actually became a neuroscientist.
>> But grief is this perpetual feeling of
like, "Oh, like I can't smell the person
or the thing. There are there glasses
and I can't do any." This is this
yearning piece and how that needs to
remap and the kind of work that we can
actually do to in a healthy way remap
that grief circuitry. And then how the
notion of somebody that we lost or a pet
perhaps gets reframed in our mind as a
not actionable now but we still have a
relationship with kind of concept and
it's a to me that was an important thing
to include.
But the big one for me was there seems
to be this contradiction in the
self-help literature and psychology
which is about half of the stuff you see
is like get after it like suck it up
fulfill your roles in life don't be a
lazy piece of [__] exercise do all you
know and then the other half is like
don't just do and drift from yourself
your true self your core self your
essential self so I think many years ago
I could have really used this chapter
that was basically it was like I could
have used all the chapters. I had sleep
issues. I so I could have used that
chapter. I could have used the stress
chap all of it. A lot of the science
wasn't known. This book would have been
impossible. But when Jim Hollis, this
incredible young psychoanalyst, came on
the podcast, he was, you know, 84 years
old then, 86 now. And I expected him to
talk about like essential self and
heart's desire. He wrote under Saturn
shadow on the healing and trauma of men.
He also wrote the Eden Project about
relationships and the struggle of
relationships and romantic
relationships. And I expected him to
give me all this kind of highle stuff,
deep heartfelt stuff. And he basically
nailed it. He said, "You have to shut
up, suit up, and show up." And I go,
"Okay, that sounds like kind of boomer
advice." He goes, "No, but it's not what
you think." He's like, "Stop
complaining. Somebody's definitely
suffering more than you." That one's
about gratitude.
>> So it's not exactly shut up. It's
be grateful for something. You're alive.
You have to get to that level when
you're suffering.
>> Mhm.
>> Cool. It ratchets out from there.
There's a lot of data on gratitude as we
know. Then there's suit up. Like we have
to be prepared. Like we need to learn to
prepare ourselves. Prepare. It's not
just about clean your room. I mean that
too. But it's about we have to prepare
ourselves to show up. We have to get
into a headsp space. We have to develop
processes that allow us to show up in
our different roles. And then we need to
show up for those roles. We need to
fulfill roles.
And you know I done a lot of role
fulfillment in my life you know as you
have too and
super important like if somebody's a
drift that we have to do this and he
explains how critical this is to our
psyche how critical it is to our
feelings of selfworth and then he also
has this other thing about how
critically important it is to ideally
once a day but at least a few times a
week to get out of the stimulus and
response that is you know shut up suit
up show up and really touch to what's
true for you, like what he calls your
heart's desires. This was more of the
Hollist that I expected, you know, and
how just quieting the mind, not feeling
like you have to do anything in that
moment allows things to come up from
your unconscious that lets you really
ask yourself. And he used these examples
like, "Is the 40-year marriage I've been
in really the one I want to be in?"
Because I made the example of like, how
beautiful is that? people say and he's
like yeah but there are a lot of people
who end life after these long marriages
and they're like I don't really want to
be in it the tragedy of that right and
how much better it would have been that
people can identify who they really are
what they really want like really touch
into what's important to them and I was
like [__] this sounds so simple and yet
that's hard work
>> simple not easy
>> simple not easy and how important it is
to do both
>> and I thought well this chapter might be
boringly simple
But that's the important work and there
lot you could take any number of
different self-help books and kind of
bin them into those or different
chapters into those. So the book again
protocols easy to remember protocols and
operating manual for the human body. The
pub date
>> September 15th
>> September 15 and I think most people
will know at this point but where should
people find more about Dr. Hubman
online?
>> Thanks. If you put Huberman Lab into the
internet, you'll probably see some stuff
that's not true and you'll probably also
find a website called Huberman Lab where
we have AI links to episodes and the
book is going to be wherever you know
you can find the book and the Hubman Lab
site is actually I have to say the team
has done a great job with that. It'll
take you to specific timestamps. If you
want to know about like dopamine and
exercise, it'll take you to those
specific timestamps. I'm really proud of
the team they've put up with me while
writing this book and all the rest. And
yeah, I mean, I'm I'm out there. And I
also am really excited about the young
upstarts who are, you know, coming for
our jobs. And, you know, you can have
mine. Andrew's going to fight it out
with you guys.
>> I'm not going to fight it out. I
[laughter] saw when you watch the Dean
Potter movie, right, you will realize
why it is a bad idea to try and prevent
the person coming up the ladder. Don't
kick out the rungs behind you. And in
his case, especially if that person is
Alex Hold, you're going to lose.
>> [laughter]
>> Andrew, great to see you as always.
Thanks for taking the time, man.
>> Thank you. I have tremendous respect and
admiration for you. I don't think I'd be
podcasting or here at all were it not
for you. And I'm a fan. I consider you a
friend. I'm very, very, very grateful to
you. Thank you for everything you're
doing.
>> Yeah, we should break bread at some
point while I'm in this neck of the
planet. And for everybody watching,
[laughter]
>> as always, Tim.
Huberman. Just look for the most recent.
You'll be able to find all the links.
We'll we will have a lot of links to
studies to MIT eye masks. We're gonna
have if they exist. I'm not even sure.
>> They do actually. I think they're a
small company.
>> Yeah, for sure. So, we'll link to
everything. You can find it there. And
as per usual, until next time, be a bit
kinder than is necessary to others.
Dramatic flourish with the eyeglasses
back on, but also to yourself. And until
next time, thanks for tuning in. See you
next time.